<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gyan passed down from one batch to another</title>
    <description>Gyan passed down from one batch to another</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 19:15:15 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 19:15:15 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice on Computer Science - Vinay Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;'/assets/img/authors/vinay_bhat.jpg'&quot; alt=&quot;Vinay Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hi, my name is Vinay Bhat and I’m a final year undergraduate student in the IT department. This summer I had interned at Siemens Research Labs, Bangalore. I had applied there because it involved the field of Artificial Intelligence, which I’m greatly interested in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I am a part of IEEE club in campus, a senior from my club forwarded this opportunity to us. I applied and sent my resume, after which there were about two telephonic interviews and I was selected for the internship.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;work-culture&quot;&gt;Work Culture&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Work culture here at Siemens was really...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vinay-siemens/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vinay-siemens/</guid>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mathworks Internship Experience</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; Taking the path less trodden (Formal methods and my Internship at MathWorks Inc) &lt;br /&gt; -Natasha Y Jeppu &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;I am a final year BTech Computer Science student. I did my second year summer internship at MathWorks Inc. Bangalore. I worked on formal methods for system verification during my internship there and helped develop a library for MathWorks Simulink Design Verifier (SLDV).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure all of you are quite confused by now of the words I used up here. I myself was introduced to these terms at the end of my first year, when I helped my Dad...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 13:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/natasha-mathworks/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/natasha-mathworks/</guid>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Insight 2k17 - CompSoc</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;insight-2k17---compsoc-talk&quot;&gt;Insight 2k17 - CompSoc Talk&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Insight 2k17, the first event for IEEE NITK Student Chapter started off with a huge response from the Computer Science Community at NITK with a jam-packed hall of students turning up to attend the talk given by final years. The talk was mainly focussed on tips and tricks to apply for research and industry internships off-campus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/insight-2k17/crowd.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crowd for Insight&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The talk was given by three final years:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;Natasha Jeppu - DAAD Wise Scholar (Interned in Germany) and Mathworks.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Ananda Rao - CSE Topper and interned at IIT Bombay and Google...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/insight-2k17/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/insight-2k17/</guid>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        <category>Insight</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Internships Abroad</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;daad&quot;&gt;DAAD&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.daad.de/deutschland/stipendium/datenbank/en/21148-scholarship-database/?daad=1&amp;amp;detail=50015295&amp;amp;origin=4&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;q=wise&amp;amp;status=1&amp;amp;subjectGrps&quot;&gt;DAAD WISE&lt;/a&gt; scholarship provides an opportunity for students to apply to colleges in Germany.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-you-need&quot;&gt;What you need:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;CGPA of 8.5/10 above as per the website&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;An acceptance from a professor in Germany (Mail as many professors as possible, some may not reply and some reply really late, so start immediately)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;application-requirements&quot;&gt;Application requirements:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;Online application form - (available once the portal opens, it’s a long form, fill it in carefully)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Your resume or CV&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;DAAD form “Certificate of Enrolment”) filled in by home institution as proof of current enrolment (available on the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/internships-Abroad/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/internships-Abroad/</guid>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A talk with - Vijayakrishna Naganoor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/vk-interview/vk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;VK Photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;why-signal-processing-why-not-core-electrical-what-fascinated-you-take-up-sp&quot;&gt;Why signal processing? Why not core electrical? What fascinated you take up SP?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Honestly, in the beginning of my second year, I just decided to choose a topic and go deep into it so that it will help me fetch an internship easily. Having a few projects related to music processing in mind, I decided to learn more about Signal Processing. With the recent boom in Machine Learning applications in SP, I realized that there were a lot of problem statements which could be taken up even at the B.Tech level. Having developed this interest in SP, I decided to...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 05:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vk-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vk-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>Gyan</category>
        
        <category>SPS</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Peeking into a hacker's mind - an Interview with Kishor Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/kishor-bhat-interview/kishor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kishor Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As our world becomes increasingly networked, protecting these networks is no longer optional. A majority of today’s companies are insufficiently prepared for a cyber attack. Unfortunately, very few in NITK have cyber-security as their interest.I hope this interview with Kishor Bhat ,a cyber-security enthusiast motivates the readers into understanding the importance of cyber security in today’s digital world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;1-how-important-are-ctfs-to-a-security-enthusiast-give-an-account-of-your-experiences-from-playing-ctfs&quot;&gt;1. How important are CTFs to a security enthusiast? Give an account of your experiences from playing CTFs&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In my opinion, pretty important.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, CTFs or Capture the Flag contests are security competitions that...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/kishor-bhat-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/kishor-bhat-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>Cyber Security</category>
        
        <category>CTFs</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A talk with - Abin Alex Pothen</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/abin-alex-interview/abin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abin Alex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;back-story&quot;&gt;Back-Story&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello guys, today I had a great opportunity to interview Abin Alex Pothen. He has done his BTech in Mechanical from NITK. He was an executive member of IEEE and SIGHT Chair in 2015. He is currently a Project Assistant at IISc and is working on non-linear control. With the amount of experience he possesses and the ‘air of intelligence’ he creates around the person he is interacting with, it was a great opportunity for me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-one-thing-you-want-mechanical-students-to-remember&quot;&gt;What is one thing you want mechanical students to remember?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;That question can be answered in...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/abin-alex-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/abin-alex-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>Research</category>
        
        <category>Gyan</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A talk with - Gaurav Hegde</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/gaurav_hegde_interview/Gaurav.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gaurav Hegde&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;back-story&quot;&gt;Back-Story&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello guys, I am Abijith, third year EEE. I had this opportunity among many opportunities to interview and talk to Gaurav. In my two years of IEEE and NITK life, I have been in touch with him for only one semester, because he took a semester off in his 7th semester. That semester has been the best academic semester for me. The discussions, the treats, the interactions, the projects, the amount of knowledge that this person has! Oh good lord!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anyway, without any further ado, presenting Gaurav. Note: Questions are in &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/gaurav-hegde-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/gaurav-hegde-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>Math</category>
        
        <category>Gyan</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice on Computer Science - Vinay Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/gyan/assets/img/vinay-bhat-interview/vinay_bhat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vinay Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-do-you-think-should-be-done-in-college-to-enhance-your-resume&quot;&gt;Q. What do you think should be done in college to enhance your resume?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ans: One should Work hard to get a high GPA. An important aspect is to work on side projects as well-course projects or your own projects. Small projects help you understand and complete learning. It is ideal to contribute to Big Open Source repositories to understand big projects. Best thing is to try to leverage these projects into your first internship. It is more important to learn one language properly rather than every langauge and not master any one of...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vinay-bhat-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/gyan/vinay-bhat-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
