<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2017 23:06:27 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2017 23:06:27 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fluid mechanics in everyday life</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;applying-makeup&quot;&gt;Applying Makeup!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/fluid-mech-everyday-life/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When you put on eye shadow or powder, you are most definitely applying shear and pressure forces. When you put foundation on a sponge and smear it over your face you can feel the shear stress acting on your face. Furthermore, the shear stress increases as the foundation moves from the sponge to your face. This causes no slip at the boundary, which allows the foundation to stick to your face rather than slide off. This is a great example of Couette Flow!!! It is amazing to realize how much fluid mechanics applies...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2017 17:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluid-mechanics-in-everyday-life/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluid-mechanics-in-everyday-life/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Fluid Mechanics</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Fourth Industrial Revolution</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Automation, Internet of Things, Genetic engineering, cloud computing, renewable energy, sustainable development. Welcome to the Future. Welcome to the 4th Industrial revolution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/the-fourth-industrial-revolution/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Professor Klaus Schwab, Founder and Executive Chairman of the World Economic Forum published the ‘The Fourth Industrial Revolution’. Through this he explained its impact on economies, countries, politics and even ideologies. The fourth industrial revolution focuses on making our industries more productive with automation cloud computing and IoT, shying away from fossil fuels and making super-soldiers (through genetic engineering!). That last one is questionable though…&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Genetic engineering will help us in not only rectifying...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 18:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-fourth-industrial-revolution/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-fourth-industrial-revolution/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        <category>Automation</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Through the eyes of a Computer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/through-the-eyes-of-a-computer/image001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Intro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robot&lt;/strong&gt; – A word that might remind you of a Rajnikanth starrer or give you the picture of a metallic body going here and there and doing things that humans do quite naturally, on their own. All of us have at least once thought of owning a robot that could do our assignments, or just do things that we are lazy to do. And then, as you enter your college, you take online courses for learning how to build robots that follow lines, identify colours and do all sorts of things that you think it should...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 18:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/through-the-eyes-of-a-computer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/through-the-eyes-of-a-computer/</guid>
        
        <category>Computer Vision</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Image Processing</category>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Reverse Engineering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am sure you would have fixed a bug if you have done programming. Going through your code, identifying places where it could have gone wrong, trying out different inputs to make it easier, each one with your own different methods! You also would have learnt to make your debugging process simpler with your experience for sure. Congratulations for your first step towards an important skill required for reverse engineering :)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lets begin with a simple intuitive understanding of reverse engineering. You have a toy gun in which you can load bullets and shoot. One fine day, it stops working!...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 17:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-reverse-engineering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-reverse-engineering/</guid>
        
        <category>CTF</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Ethical Hacking</category>
        
        <category>Security</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Implementing Google Image Search Style Grid</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;implementing-google-image-search-style-grid&quot;&gt;Implementing Google Image Search Style Grid&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;I love design principles of Google. The way they present things is really awesome. One such presentation is Google Image Search.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/google_image_search/google_image_search.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Image Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Look at the way they arrange images. Each row has a fixed width, but their are no columns. The images have arranges themselves, intelligently, just enough to fit the row. I always wondered, what algorithm they must have used to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-thought&quot;&gt;What I thought&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;So my search began. Initially I thought they might have used some kind of knapsack algorithm to fit images to...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 17:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/google-image-search-grid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/google-image-search-grid/</guid>
        
        <category>Design</category>
        
        <category>Grid</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lighting Up your Room!</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;apparatus&quot;&gt;Apparatus:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;1.&lt;strong&gt;LED strips&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt; You should find these in most home decor stores. They could turn out to be expensive depending upon the quality of light you expect. There are RGB strips available too! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2.&lt;strong&gt;TIP 31 switch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Now this is a power transistor that can withstand large currents that the LED strips demand&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;3.&lt;strong&gt;AUX cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; This is to connect your music player to the device&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;4.&lt;strong&gt;12V battery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The LED strips demand a lot of current, so get one that supplies enough. There are rechargeable lead acid batteries available. They are cheaper, but bulkier...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 16:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/lighting-up-your-room/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/lighting-up-your-room/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
        <category>SPS</category>
        
        <category>EEE</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Class of NP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of us have this notion that NP stands for “Non Polynomial”, the problems which can’t be solved in polynomial time. This is not true. First of all, NP consist of only decision problem (given any problem, the answer should be yes or no) solvable in polynomial time by a theoretical non-deterministic Turing machine. Well, I am not going to cover non-deterministic Turing machine in this blog, so I will give another verifier based definition.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;verifier-based-definition&quot;&gt;Verifier Based Definition:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consider a decision problem X. Let I be an instance of X for which the answer is “yes”. Now if we...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2017 22:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-class-of-np/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-class-of-np/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Algorithms</category>
        
        <category>P v/s NP</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Not Chemical Engineering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what kind of fascination it is, probably parents sermon their little ones or the Indian school teachers are rather pedagogues, but this one notion of securing admission for undergraduation in a leading institute with specialisation in computer science is considered to be victory. I too was once a prey to this concept. The D-day shattered my dreams and landed me to choose one among the core branches. Hence, by elimination, the same technique one might use in the exams (xD), I chose chemical.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminary thoughts:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical engineering = Chemistry. Bury myself. Very disinclined to the idea of...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 12:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-not-chemical-engineering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-not-chemical-engineering/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Chemical</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to GPU Computing</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-gamers-priced-possession---graphic-cards&quot;&gt;A Gamer’s priced possession - Graphic Cards!&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s say that you have bought a brand new computer with one of the latest i7 processors but without installing a separate graphics card. And your friend is still using his 5 year PC with an old i3 processor, but with a high end graphics card installed. Both of you play the same game simultaneously on your own computers. But you notice that the gaming performance is better on his PC even though your computer is brand new. You scratch your head not understanding what’s going on here. You have a much...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-GPU-computing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-GPU-computing/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>High Performance Computing</category>
        
        <category>Game Development</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Get Started with Bots</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-get-started-with-bots&quot;&gt;How to get Started with bots&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have you ever been fascinated by robots - Awestrucking objects which are capable of performing some cool tasks without needing a human intervention (well, unless they decide to go mad! :P) ? And certainly the thought of how these genius creations work and can I make one too? must have crossed your mind. Being in a similar frame of mind couple of years back and having made some basic bots, I thought of writing this article to help the curious people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-stuff-together&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff together&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;It’s surely hard to shell out a few...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 23:58:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-to-get-started-with-bots/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-to-get-started-with-bots/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Bots</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
