<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:44:14 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:44:14 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Washable Electronics using Water repellant Graphene Circuits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washable electronics? Water-repellent graphene circuits make it possible!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New graphene printing technology can produce electronic circuits that are low-cost, flexible, highly conductive and water repellent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/washable-electonics/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Landing image&quot; /&gt; The nanotechnology “would lend enormous value to self-cleaning wearable/washable electronics that are resistant to stains, or ice and biofilm formation,” according to a recent paper describing the discovery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;According to Jonathan Claussen, an Iowa State University assistant professor of mechanical engineering, an associate of the U.S. Department of Energy’s Ames Laboratory, they’re taking low-cost, inkjet-printed graphene and tuning it with a laser to make functional materials.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The research group used...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/washable-electonics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/washable-electonics/</guid>
        
        <category>graphene</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>QEMU/KVM for Virtual Machines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A “virtual machine” or “VM” is a virtual computer system. It is a tightly isolated software container with an operating system and application inside. Putting multiple VMs on a single computer enables several operating systems and applications to run on just one physical server, or “host.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A thin layer of software called a “hypervisor” decouples the virtual machines from the host and dynamically allocates computing resources to each virtual machine as needed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;qemu-and-kvm&quot;&gt;QEMU and KVM&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;QEMU or Quick Emulator is an open-source machine emulator and virtualizer. It can be used for full-system emulation, user-mode emulation as well...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/qemu-vitualization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/qemu-vitualization/</guid>
        
        <category>virtualization</category>
        
        <category>qemu</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Amazon Go - Cashier Less Shopping</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-amazon-go&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What exactly is Amazon Go?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Amazon Go is Amazon’s cashier-less shopping platform. Contrary to Amazon’s online website, the Go is a brick and mortar store- similar to your regular convenience store. What’s unique about the Go is that you can pick up an item and just walk out of the store without having to wait in line to pay for it. The store sells ordinary grocery items like bread, dairy and packaged ready to eat meals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/Bt-SIGm_gZkzinkwUtHNwCpmJUI=/0x0:650x370/1200x800/filters:focal(273x133:377x237)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_image/image/52140057/amazon_go.0.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A customer has to hold up a QR code on the Amazon Go app...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/amazon-go/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/amazon-go/</guid>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        <category>spatial imaging</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS/SPS</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envision Project 2: Smart Lighting Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the ongoing developments in the technological World, a lot of efforts have been invested in the field of automation to make everyone's life easier. As engineering students and the future of the World, it is our responsibility to lead the world into a better future via introducing technology which would reduce human effort as much as possible. Our project, &quot;Smart Lighting System&quot; aimed at automating the process of lighting of homes in order to personalize the control over system and to adapt itself to surroundings for better experience. So basically we decided to introduce 3 main features...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-lighting-systems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-lighting-systems/</guid>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        
        <category>Envision</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envision Project 1 - Professor Matching for Research Internships</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finding research/internship opportunity under a professor’s guidance is exceedingly difficult because the professors are very busy and students are not well aware of the professors who are ready to give internship opportunities. The professor has to shortlist the resumes and the student has to find out and send a resume to every professor offering a research opportunity. Obviously, this is a time consuming and tiresome process for both students and the professors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We came up with a idea which not only speeds up this process but also makes it hassle-free. The idea is to create a platform which...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/prof-matching-envision/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/prof-matching-envision/</guid>
        
        <category>Android</category>
        
        <category>Web</category>
        
        <category>Django</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evolution of bicycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since a person began thinking of sources of transportation, maximum development until date has been in the field of bicycle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the designs discussed briefly, innovation in them and the reasons for their failure or upgradation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first known bicycle was the &lt;strong&gt;velocipede&lt;/strong&gt;, a human powered vehicle which required the person riding it to actually push himself against the ground in order to move. No pedals, chain whatsoever, just 2 wheels, a frame and a seat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/cycle/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Archetype of a Bicycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Slowly, came an era of multi-wheeled bicycles. Improved stability, increased load carrying...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evolution-of-bicycle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evolution-of-bicycle/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electric Cars - The Future</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Should you really buy an electric car?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Electric vehicles are hitting the world’s roads and with government support behind them these are hyped up to be the next big thing in the automobile industry . Combustion engine vehicles generate huge quantities of pollution, and developed economies create more than their fair share of this. The US transportation sector accounts for around 30 percent of US global warming emissions which is an order of magnitude more than most countries. In this blog I will tell you what I think on buying an electric car.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Quick and Quiet...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/electric-cars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/electric-cars/</guid>
        
        <category>Electric Cars</category>
        
        <category>CAS/SPS</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>t-SNE</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s manually impossible to understand the structure of a dataset with 100 dimensions. And it’s fairly common to come across data having so many features. And the exploratory-analysis of data is a preliminary step, before proceeding to other aspects of data-wrangling and models. This is where t-SNE comes in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-distributed_stochastic_neighbor_embedding&quot;&gt;t-SNE&lt;/a&gt; is non-linear dimensionality reduction algorithm. It reduces each high-dimensional point and embeds them into a 2D/3D map. Additionally, it ensures that similar objects are nearby and dissimilar points are kept apart.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;uses-of-t-sne&quot;&gt;Uses of t-SNE&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;It’s hard to visualize high-dimensional objects&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Existing data-visualization techniques only enable visualization of...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/tSNE/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/tSNE/</guid>
        
        <category>Data Visualization</category>
        
        <category>t-SNE</category>
        
        <category>ML</category>
        
        <category>Data Visualization</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bit Manipulation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;All data in computer programs is internally stored as bits, i.e., as numbers 0 and 1. It turns out that there are many uses for bit manipulation in competitive programming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In programming, an n bit integer is internally stored as a binary number that consists of n bits. For example, the C++ type int is a 32-bit type, which means that every int number consists of 32 bits. For exmaple, the bit representation of the int number 42 is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;00000000000000000000000000101010&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several bit operations supported by a typical ALU, some of them being AND, OR, NOT, XOR, and...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 16:45:53 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bit-manipulation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bit-manipulation/</guid>
        
        <category>Bit masks</category>
        
        <category>DP</category>
        
        <category>Competitive Programming</category>
        
        <category>C++</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fluids and Satellites</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The increasingly large volumes of fluid that have to be carried aboard satellites designed for long operating lifetimes, but which often must also deliver high-accuracy pointing, mean that special attention has to be paid to the behavior of fluids in low gravity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;low-gravity-and-fluid-dynamics&quot;&gt;Low gravity and fluid dynamics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several methods for analyzing the dynamic behavior of fluids under normal gravity conditions on Earth. A common assumption in such methods is that the free surface of the fluid is flat and at right angles to the direction in which gravity is acting, i.e. normal to the gravity vector. In...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 16:35:53 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluids-and-satellites/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluids-and-satellites/</guid>
        
        <category>Fluid Dynamics</category>
        
        <category>Satellites</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
