<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 16:21:37 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 16:21:37 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Challenger Disaster</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;On January 28&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; 1986, the scheduled launch for NASA’s space orbiter- the Challenger, took place as planned. But the launch was the only part of the mission that stuck to plan. 73 seconds after liftoff, the shuttle exploded and broke up, bringing a devastating end to the spacecraft’s 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; mission, claiming all 7 lives onboard. All because of a tiny, rather overlooked aspect of a structure failing due to a very basic property of the given material.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After extensive failure analysis, it was determined that the failure of 2 rubber O-rings caused the disaster.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To understand why the...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2017 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/piston/2017/09/25/Challenger-disaster.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/piston/2017/09/25/Challenger-disaster.html</guid>
        
        <category>Space</category>
        
        <category>NASA</category>
        
        <category>Case Study</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What makes a Smart Home Smart</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;When you leave your home have you been bothered by these little doubts like have I turned the water heater off? Did I set the security at home? Did I switch off the TV?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the introduction of smart homes these will no longer be a bother to us anymore. Any electrical component, may it be a fan or your TV or even you’re your coffee maker, every electrical appliance in our homes can be hooked up the home network. This will basically allow us to control our entire house with our laptops or something as simple as...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2017 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/cas/ieee%20nitk/2017/09/25/What-Makes-a-Smart-Home-Smart.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/cas/ieee%20nitk/2017/09/25/What-Makes-a-Smart-Home-Smart.html</guid>
        
        <category>Smart homes</category>
        
        <category>Internet of things</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BitTorrent Explained</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;“Just torrent it!”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“You can torrent any type of file, its all there on the internet…”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;These are just some of the common sentences one hears when it comes to downloading files from the internet. However, many people do not even know what BitTorrent is, much less know how it works.(It includes uploading files as well)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;a-simple-introduction&quot;&gt;A simple introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/BitTorrent-Explained/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;BitTorrent Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;BitTorrent is a communication protocol(set of rules) that is used for sharing all types of data and electronic files over the internet. This falls under the category of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer_file_sharing&quot;&gt;peer-to-peer file sharing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now,...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2017 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/compsoc/2017/09/18/BitTorrentExplained.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/compsoc/2017/09/18/BitTorrentExplained.html</guid>
        
        <category>Networking</category>
        
        <category>Torrents</category>
        
        <category>P2P</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Storing energy in molten salt</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Renewable energy is the answer to sustainable development. It is the hot topic of our generation and even though it is in its rudimentary stage, it is the best solution in maintaining the balance between environment and our energy needs. We all know that a lot of research is going on in this field, whether it is the oft talked about and used solar and wind energy, or the slightly less used ocean thermal energy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But, what do you do after you produce this energy? What if it is in excess to your current need? You need to...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2017 15:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/piston/2017/09/18/storing-energy-in-salt!.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/piston/2017/09/18/storing-energy-in-salt!.html</guid>
        
        <category>Energy</category>
        
        <category>Research</category>
        
        <category>Innovation</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Water Memory, What A Memory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What would you preferably use to store your precious data- a hard disk, a pen-drive, a DVD; or perhaps WATER!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Scientists from Germany now believe that water has a memory, meaning that what once was seen as a simple commodity has been closely examined to reveal a scientific revelation, uncovering a mind-blowing truth.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;theory&quot;&gt;Theory&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Individual drops of water from the same sample were examined at incredibly high magnification, probably the first experiment of this kind and surprisingly scientists were able to physically see that each droplet of water has its own &lt;em&gt;individual microscopic pattern,&lt;/em&gt; distinguishable from the next and...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/cas/ieee%20nitk/2017/09/11/Water-Memory,-What-A-Memory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/cas/ieee%20nitk/2017/09/11/Water-Memory,-What-A-Memory.html</guid>
        
        <category>Water memory</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rock Paper Scissors</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have ever played the game of rock, paper scissors I bet that the best strategy you had was trying to predict your opponent’s move which is a pretty appealing idea. But given that it is nigh impossible to do that (unless, of course, you can read minds), is that really a sound strategy to adopt? If you think about it in a rational way there is no method to predict your opponent and basing your strategy on such an unpredictable thing is kind of dumb. I think the best approach to this problem is to make sure your...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/cas/2017/09/04/Rock-Paper-Scissors.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/cas/2017/09/04/Rock-Paper-Scissors.html</guid>
        
        <category>Game Theory</category>
        
        <category>Strategy</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Airbus E-Fan</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-airbus-e-fan-project&quot;&gt;The Airbus E-Fan Project&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;For over a hundred years - and certainly many to follow, the aircraft industry, for the most part, has relied upon combustion based engines, ranging from the long-forgotten piston-prop through the state of the art Turbofan. Yet, no matter what the degree of advancement is in the field of such engines, what’s guaranteed is an ever-increasing toll of CO2 and other greenhouse gases.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The intuitive solution for sustainable development, as in nearly all domains of power generation, especially in transportation, is electricity. Presently, every mode of transport (save for aviation) employs at least a certain...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/piston/2017/09/04/Airbus-E-Fan.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/piston/2017/09/04/Airbus-E-Fan.html</guid>
        
        <category>Aviation</category>
        
        <category>Environment</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Safety Issues in AI Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure the title will flood the reader’s mind with images of Skynet and Matrix, but this post focuses on the shortcomings of AI technologies that are currently in vogue. It’s much more productive to contemplate on the loopholes in technologies like Neural Networks, as we are still a far cry from building systems that are at least as intelligent as earthworms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;AI has made several inroads into diverse fields such as NLP, Computer Vision, Autonomous Vehicles, Personal Assistants, and Game playing bots. AI has become truly ubiquitous. This magnifies the impact of security loopholes on the society....</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 02:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/compsoc/2017/09/04/Safety-Issues-in-AI-Systems.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/compsoc/2017/09/04/Safety-Issues-in-AI-Systems.html</guid>
        
        <category>ML</category>
        
        <category>AI</category>
        
        <category>Security AI</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technology in Sports</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The world of sport is continually changing over the years, and the use of technology is just one of those areas that has made an impact on many sports. It has changed the way players approach a particular sport. Various technologies are used to assist umpires or referees, while some of them are used for advanced coaching and enhanced experience for fans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;a-digital-coach&quot;&gt;A digital coach…&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the recently concluded Champions Trophy 2017, smart bats were used to obtain various data. Small sensors, fixed at the top of the handle, were used. The bat sensor, powered by the Intel Curie technology,...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 04:45:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/diode/2017/08/22/Technology-in-Sports.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/diode/2017/08/22/Technology-in-Sports.html</guid>
        
        <category>Sports</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hashing in Competitive Programming</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;At it’s most basic hashing is a technique to identify a particular value of a certain type among other values of the same type. To achieve this we typically make use of a hash function: a function that takes a value of the required type as input and generates a “key” that (hopefully) can uniquely identify this value. In this article we’ll look at how this function works, how it’s implemented in C++, and how to apply hashing to solve a Competitive Programming problem.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;hashing-in-c&quot;&gt;Hashing in C++&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;C++ offers 2 containers in C++ that are often useful...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 01:10:58 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/compsoc/2017/08/22/Hashing-in-Competitive-Programming.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/compsoc/2017/08/22/Hashing-in-Competitive-Programming.html</guid>
        
        <category>Hashing</category>
        
        <category>C++</category>
        
        <category>Competitive Programming</category>
        
        <category>Data Structures</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
