<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2018 20:28:36 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2018 20:28:36 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>NanoMedicine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How evolutionary is nanomedicine in therapeutics? Is it worth all the hype? Can we, as engineers, find opportunities in the field of nanomedicine? Well, I hope this article will answer many similar questions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/NanoMedicine/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nanopills: Medicinal advantage&quot; title=&quot;Nanopills: Medicinal advantage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;nanotechnology-and-its-manifestation-in-medicine&quot;&gt;Nanotechnology and its manifestation in Medicine&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/NanoMedicine/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Manifestation of Nanotechnology in Medicine&quot; title=&quot;Manifestation of Nanotechnology in Medicine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the understanding of how exactly is nanotechnology playing a noteworthy role in the field of medicine. From its very dawn, nanotechnology has indeed shaped the fundamental industrial applications such as manufacturing, biotechnology, semiconductors and fabrication...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/NanoMedicine/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/NanoMedicine/</guid>
        
        <category>NanoMedicine</category>
        
        <category>Targeted drug delivery</category>
        
        <category>Overlooked advancements</category>
        
        <category>EPR effect</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Computers learn to play games!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered how computers learn to play games like Chess or Go? Or how do they replace human players in Ludo or Card games? How Google’s Alpha-Go defeated the &lt;strong&gt;World Champion&lt;/strong&gt; of Go? Let us dive in the field of Computer Games and find out how Computers learn to play Games!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/How Computers LearnToPlayGames/chess.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chess&quot; title=&quot;Chess&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are various algorithms that are used to make a computer learn to play games. I will be discussing some of them to give you some intuition on how these algorithms work.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;naive-tree-search&quot;&gt;Naive Tree Search&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/How-Computers-learn-to-play-games/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/How-Computers-learn-to-play-games/</guid>
        
        <category>Computer Games</category>
        
        <category>Reinforcement Learning</category>
        
        <category>Monte Carlo Tree Search</category>
        
        <category>Alpha-Go</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GaN: Gate to New era</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;gan-gate-to-new-era&quot;&gt;GaN: Gate to New era&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/GaN/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;introduction&quot; title=&quot;Introduction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To make life easier, more affordable mankind has always been in search of transforming the current technologies and making it much more better, whether be it wheels to cars, or electric current to cell phones. Different tech giants use slogans such as ‘Be what’s next’ by Microsoft, ‘THINK’ by IBM, etc, thus directly promoting new transformations not only in technology but they point towards an economical product which is easily feasible and accessible to its customers. Since the dawn of the electronics age over a hundred years ago, power...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/GaN/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/GaN/</guid>
        
        <category>galliumnitride</category>
        
        <category>GaN</category>
        
        <category>transistors</category>
        
        <category>wafers</category>
        
        <category>silicon</category>
        
        <category>newsilicon</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why you should learn Flutter?</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-flutter&quot;&gt;What is Flutter?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Flutter is an open-source Mobile Application Development SDK launched by Google back in May 2017. It is used to create apps for both Android and iOS Operating Systems. It is also the primary method of developing applications for Google Fuchsia. Flutter 1.0 was announced on December 4th, 2018 at &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/events/flutter-live/&quot;&gt;Flutter Live&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;why-flutter&quot;&gt;Why Flutter?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incredibly easy to setup and get started!&lt;/strong&gt; - Download the Flutter SDK from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://flutter.io/docs/get-started/install&quot;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt;. Extract it and add the flutter sdk path to your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; variable. Download the Flutter plugin in your favourite editor / IDE and...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-you-should-learn-flutter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-you-should-learn-flutter/</guid>
        
        <category>Flutter</category>
        
        <category>Android</category>
        
        <category>Dart</category>
        
        <category>Cross platform mobile development</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nanosheets decorated with DNA</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;nanosheets-decorated-with-dna&quot;&gt;NANOSHEETS DECORATED WITH DNA&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;One possible means of bridging the gap between India’s abundant, varied natural resources and her ever-increasing requirements like clean water, food and rapid, low cost diagnostic machinery is the use of nanotechnology. When we modify materials at their atomic and molecular level, some very unusual and useful properties are generated. Since the dimensions of atoms and molecule are in nanometers, this technology is called nanotechnology. Efforts to promote research in nanotechnology in India began early in the millennium. The efforts have paid off well, India published over 23000 papers in nanoscience in the past 5...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanosheets-decorated-with-dna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanosheets-decorated-with-dna/</guid>
        
        <category>Nanosheets</category>
        
        <category>DNA</category>
        
        <category>Nanotechnology</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electronic skin</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;electronic-skin&quot;&gt;ELECTRONIC SKIN&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/electronic-skin/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hand with electronic skin&quot; title=&quot;Hand with electronic skin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Touch is the first sense we acquire and has been shown to play a crucial role in physical and mental health. The nerve cells in our skin allow us to experience the several experiences of touch such as a cold splash of water, the tug of a strong breeze or the heat from your coffee mug. Scientists are trying to develop electronic skin to help robots and prosthetic devices to attain these abilities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Researchers report a new method in &lt;em&gt;ACS Applied Materials &amp;amp; Interfaces&lt;/em&gt; that creates...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electonic-skin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electonic-skin/</guid>
        
        <category>Electronic</category>
        
        <category>Skin</category>
        
        <category>Healthcare</category>
        
        <category>Robotics</category>
        
        <category>Embedded</category>
        
        <category>Prosthetic</category>
        
        <category>Sensor</category>
        
        <category>Stretchable</category>
        
        <category>Nanoparticles</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>NanoMachines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article provides a brief insight in the field of nanomachines and nanosensors, the challenges faced by the researchers in this field, and the promise they hold for us in future applications&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-difference-between-micro-and-nano-systems&quot;&gt;What is the difference between micro and nano systems?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we talk about about nanomachines, we consider devices which are only a few atoms apart in their dimensions whereas in microsystems, the dimensions are in the range of a few microns. Thus, these devices can only be observed under &lt;strong&gt;HR-TEM (High Resolution Tunneling Electron Microscope)&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;thermal imaging techniques.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/nanomachines/2-nanocars.png&quot; alt=&quot;A nano car developed by RICE...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanomachines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanomachines/</guid>
        
        <category>MEMS</category>
        
        <category>NEMS</category>
        
        <category>Nanotechnology</category>
        
        <category>Biomedics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gesture Controlled Robot</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&quot;JARVIS, Suit me Up!&quot;, &quot;Clang! Spoof! Phew!&quot;, Tony Stark becomes IRON MAN!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have You Ever Wondered, what if, just like that, with one cool move you too could control and move objects around you; OR Maybe develop a gesture-controlled game like in the movie Ra. One? Well, here I have tried to design and build a mini version of it; a Robot controlled by hand gestures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But first up, what exactly is a Gesture Controlled Robot?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Robot which detects any movement(gesture) and functions depending upon these signals is a Gesture Controlled Robot. They can use different technologies viz. accelerometer-based...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/gesture_controlled_robot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/gesture_controlled_robot/</guid>
        
        <category>Gesture controlled</category>
        
        <category>accelerometer</category>
        
        <category>RF transmitter</category>
        
        <category>RF receiver</category>
        
        <category>motor driver</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cloud Gaming</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Till today gaming had been possible only on dedicated machines like PCs, gaming consoles like nintendo, playstations and xbox and in the recent times on mobile phones too. But even today the AAA titles or the large budget games like Assassin’s Creed Unity, GTA 5 are only available on consoles and PCs(only windows), but a new technology is emerging today which aims to break all barriers and bring AAA gaming to all devices alike(yes, even to mac and linux). Read on to find what this new &lt;strong&gt;awesome tech&lt;/strong&gt; is all about and how you can get a glimpse of the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-gaming/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-gaming/</guid>
        
        <category>Gaming</category>
        
        <category>Cloud</category>
        
        <category>Google Project Stream</category>
        
        <category>Nvidia Now</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MicroLED</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-future-of-television&quot;&gt;The Future of Television?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Recently at the CES(Consumers Electronics Show) 2018 Samsung unveiled its prototype of the MicroLED at the consumer level with a 146inch MicroLED TV under the name “The Wall”. MicroLED technology was invented in the year 2000 by a research group run by Prof. Hongxing Jiang and Prof. Jingyu Lin of the Texas Tech University. However, the first demonstration of MicroLED as a consumer product can be traced back to Sony’s 55-inch FullHD “Crystal LED Display” that was showcased back in 2012. This was incredibly expensive and was not viable on a commercial scale....</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/microled/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/microled/</guid>
        
        <category>LED</category>
        
        <category>Television</category>
        
        <category>Micro</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
