<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 19:11:35 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 19:11:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organic Photovoltaics</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;organic-photovoltaics&quot;&gt;Organic Photovoltaics&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-&quot;&gt;Introduction :&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Photovoltaics is the process of directly converting sunlight into electricity without any heat engine to interfere. Photovoltaic devices are rugged and simple in design requiring very little maintenance and their biggest advantage being their construction as stand-alone systems to give outputs from microwatts to megawatts. Hence they are used for a vast array of applications resulting in the increase in demand for photovoltaics. Recently, ORGANIC PHOTOVOLTAICS (OPV), has been the subject of active research as this technology has the potential to spawn a new generation of low-cost, solar-powered products with thin and flexible form...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/organic-photovoltaics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/organic-photovoltaics/</guid>
        
        <category>Organic Photovoltaics</category>
        
        <category>Excitons</category>
        
        <category>Photo-active layer</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MEMS</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;mems-micro-electro-mechanical-systems&quot;&gt;MEMS (Micro Electro Mechanical Systems)&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;An introduction to field of micro systems and their applications.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“There is plenty of room at the bottom.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article deals with the emerging field of micro-electromechanical systems, or MEMS. MEMS is a process technology used to create tiny integrated devices or systems that combine mechanical and electrical components. These devices (or systems) can sense, control and actuate on the micro scale, and generate effects on the macro scale. MEMS has been identified as one of the most promising technologies for the 21st Century and has the potential...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/mems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/mems/</guid>
        
        <category>MEMS</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Demystifying Deconvolutions</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;demystifying-deconvolutions&quot;&gt;Demystifying Deconvolutions&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article mainly discusses about &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up-sampling with Deconvolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’ve heard about the term Deconvolution, and are willing to learn more about it, please read on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The contents of the this article is as follows:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The need for Up-sampling&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convolution Operation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Going backward&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convolution Matrix&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Transposed Convolution Matrix&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Deconvolution is also known as &lt;strong&gt;Transposed Convolution&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Fractionally-strided Convolution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-need-for-up-sampling&quot;&gt;The need for Up-sampling&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we use neural networks to process or generate images, there is a decrease in the size of the intermediate images in the subsequent layers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/deconv/p1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when an...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/deconv/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/deconv/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Convolution</category>
        
        <category>Up-sampling</category>
        
        <category>Neural Networks</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Supercapacitors</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A supercapacitor is a specially designed capacitor which has an enormous capacitance. While capacitors used in everyday life tend to have values in the nano or microfarad range, supercapacitors can have values of upto 12,000 F depending on their application.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/supercap/img1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;img1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;construction&quot;&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Like an ordinary capacitor, a supercapacitor has two plates that are separated. The plates are made from metal coated with a porous substance such as powdery, activated charcoal, which effectively gives them a bigger area for storing much more charge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What about the separator between the plates? In an ordinary capacitor, the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/supercap/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/supercap/</guid>
        
        <category>Supercapacitors</category>
        
        <category>Energy Storage</category>
        
        <category>Futurology</category>
        
        <category>Batteries</category>
        
        <category>Renewables</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drive By Wire</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;drive-by-wire&quot;&gt;Drive-by-wire&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Drive by wire is a catch all term that can refer to a number of electronic systems that take either augment or completely replace traditional mechanical controls.Instead of using cables, hydraulic pressure and other ways of providing a driver with direct, physical control over the speed or direction of a vehicle, drive-by-wire technology uses electronic controls to activate the brakes, controls the steering, and operate other systems.Although it’s well-established in the airline industry, drive-by-wire has been slow in its introduction to the car. &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/by_wire/fig1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fig1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;throttle-by-wire&quot;&gt;Throttle by wire&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;A typical Electronic Throttle Control(ETC) system consists...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/by-wire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/by-wire/</guid>
        
        <category>Drive by wire</category>
        
        <category>Steer by wire</category>
        
        <category>Autonomous vehicle</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>KMP Algorithm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to talk about an algorithm that I believe should be in any Software Engineer’s toolkit. That is, the KMP algorithm named after its three inventors: Knuth-Morris-Pratt. The algorithm was designed to solve efficiently a very common problem. That is the problem of finding whether or not one string is a substring of a different string.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;brute-force&quot;&gt;Brute Force&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s start first with the original problem. We would like to implement the function: int strstr(const string &amp;amp;Str, const string&amp;amp; Pattern); The brute force solution of this function entails two loops, one over Str and one over pattern. Let’s see...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/KMP-Algorithm/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/KMP-Algorithm/</guid>
        
        <category>KMP</category>
        
        <category>Strings</category>
        
        <category>Competitive Programming</category>
        
        <category>C++</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coronary Stents</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-coronary-stents--work&quot;&gt;How coronary stents work?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Brief Breakdown On One Of The Most Frequented Surgeries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how exactly stents are used during or after an angioplasty? Why did this method replace bypass surgeries for minor heart attacks ? Well, read on to comprehend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-coronary-artery-disease-cad&quot;&gt;What is coronary artery disease (CAD)?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;CAD happens when a waxy substance called plaque builds up on the inner walls of the coronary arteries. This causes the arteries to harden and narrow, decreasing blood flow to the heart. As a result , the heart doesnt getthe blood, oxygen and nutrients it needs, which can lead...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:12:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/coronary-stents/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/coronary-stents/</guid>
        
        <category>heart</category>
        
        <category>disease</category>
        
        <category>treatment</category>
        
        <category>surgeries</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electronic Aspirin</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;electronic-aspirin&quot;&gt;ELECTRONIC ASPIRIN&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;For people who suffer from migraines, cluster headaches and other causes of chronic, excruciating head or facial pain, the &quot;take two aspirins and call me in the morning&quot; method is useless. Doctors have long associated the most severe, chronic forms of headache with the sphenopalatine ganglion (SPG), a facial nerve bundle, but haven't yet found a treatment that works on the SPG long-term.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, there is technology for the rescue: &lt;strong&gt;The Electronic Aspirin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is a patient-powered tool for blocking SPG signals at the first sign of a headache.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It consists of two components. A...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:03:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electronic-aspirin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electronic-aspirin/</guid>
        
        <category>electronics</category>
        
        <category>neurostimulators</category>
        
        <category>remote control</category>
        
        <category>SPG</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web 3.0: The upcoming Web revolution</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-30-what-in-the-world-is-that&quot;&gt;Web 3.0?? What in the world is that???!!!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a lot of buzz around web 3.0 and the changes it can bring in the world of tech. But only a few know what it actually is…Before hopping into web 3.0 let us know a little about its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Web 1.0&lt;/em&gt; , which started the whole damn internet and the &lt;em&gt;Web 2.0&lt;/em&gt; that we all use and love so much. Web 1.0 was just a set of &lt;em&gt;static websites&lt;/em&gt; . It comprised of a load of websites with no interactive information. But as the internet got faster and...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-3-0/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-3-0/</guid>
        
        <category>Web 3.0</category>
        
        <category>Ethereum</category>
        
        <category>Blockchains</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vortices</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;vortices&quot;&gt;Vortices&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;When everything seems to be going against you, remember that an airplane takes off against the wind, not with it&lt;/em&gt;” – Henry Ford&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article has been written especially for those who are interested in aerodynamics and also for people who are curious to know how small modifications in design help make an airplane or a car more aerodynamically efficient. The content is from an aerodynamic point of view, in an airflow.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/vortices/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fig.1&quot; title=&quot;Fig.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Vortex (Fig. 1) is nothing but a region in a fluid which revolves about a certain axis. These...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 02:50:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/vortices/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/vortices/</guid>
        
        <category>aerodynamics</category>
        
        <category>vortex</category>
        
        <category>formula 1</category>
        
        <category>aviation</category>
        
        <category>flight</category>
        
        <category>airflow</category>
        
        <category>fluids</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
