<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 14:15:38 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 14:15:38 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>NanoMachines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article provides a brief insight in the field of nanomachines and nanosensors, the challenges faced by the researchers in this field, and the promise they hold for us in future applications&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-difference-between-micro-and-nano-systems&quot;&gt;What is the difference between micro and nano systems?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we talk about about nanomachines, we consider devices which are only a few atoms apart in their dimensions whereas in microsystems, the dimensions are in the range of a few microns. Thus, these devices can only be observed under &lt;strong&gt;HR-TEM (High Resolution Tunneling Electron Microscope)&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;thermal imaging techniques.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/nanomachines/2-nanocars.png&quot; alt=&quot;A nano car developed by RICE...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanomachines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanomachines/</guid>
        
        <category>MEMS</category>
        
        <category>NEMS</category>
        
        <category>Nanotechnology</category>
        
        <category>Biomedics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gesture Controlled Robot</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&quot;JARVIS, Suit me Up!&quot;, &quot;Clang! Spoof! Phew!&quot;, Tony Stark becomes IRON MAN!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have You Ever Wondered, what if, just like that, with one cool move you too could control and move objects around you; OR Maybe develop a gesture-controlled game like in the movie Ra. One? Well, here I have tried to design and build a mini version of it; a Robot controlled by hand gestures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But first up, what exactly is a Gesture Controlled Robot?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Robot which detects any movement(gesture) and functions depending upon these signals is a Gesture Controlled Robot. They can use different technologies viz. accelerometer-based...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/gesture_controlled_robot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/gesture_controlled_robot/</guid>
        
        <category>Gesture controlled</category>
        
        <category>accelerometer</category>
        
        <category>RF transmitter</category>
        
        <category>RF receiver</category>
        
        <category>motor driver</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cloud Gaming</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Till today gaming had been possible only on dedicated machines like PCs, gaming consoles like nintendo, playstations and xbox and in the recent times on mobile phones too. But even today the AAA titles or the large budget games like Assassin’s Creed Unity, GTA 5 are only available on consoles and PCs(only windows), but a new technology is emerging today which aims to break all barriers and bring AAA gaming to all devices alike(yes, even to mac and linux). Read on to find what this new &lt;strong&gt;awesome tech&lt;/strong&gt; is all about and how you can get a glimpse of the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-gaming/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-gaming/</guid>
        
        <category>Gaming</category>
        
        <category>Cloud</category>
        
        <category>Google Project Stream</category>
        
        <category>Nvidia Now</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MicroLED</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-future-of-television&quot;&gt;The Future of Television?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Recently at the CES(Consumers Electronics Show) 2018 Samsung unveiled its prototype of the MicroLED at the consumer level with a 146inch MicroLED TV under the name “The Wall”. MicroLED technology was invented in the year 2000 by a research group run by Prof. Hongxing Jiang and Prof. Jingyu Lin of the Texas Tech University. However, the first demonstration of MicroLED as a consumer product can be traced back to Sony’s 55-inch FullHD “Crystal LED Display” that was showcased back in 2012. This was incredibly expensive and was not viable on a commercial scale....</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/microled/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/microled/</guid>
        
        <category>LED</category>
        
        <category>Television</category>
        
        <category>Micro</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ballistics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ballistics is the science of the propulsion, flight, and impact of projectiles especially bullets, unguided bombs or rockets. It is divided into several disciplines. &lt;em&gt;Internal and external ballistics&lt;/em&gt;, respectively, deal with the propulsion and the flight of projectiles. The transition between these two regimes is called &lt;em&gt;intermediate ballistics&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Terminal ballistics&lt;/em&gt; concerns the impact of projectiles which is a separate category that study the wounding of personnel&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;internal-ballistics&quot;&gt;Internal Ballistics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A fire arm cartridge contains four components namely &lt;em&gt;Primer, Case, Propellent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Bullet__.&lt;/em&gt; The basic working of a fire arm is that when the trigger is pressed the firing pin of...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ballistics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ballistics/</guid>
        
        <category>Ballistics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zero Knowledge Proof</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/ZeroKnowledgeProof/introduction.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In cryptography, &lt;em&gt;zero knowledge proof&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;zero knowledge protocol&lt;/em&gt; is a method by which one party proves to another party that they know some kind of secret without revealing any information about the secret, except the fact that they know it. This principle is based on an algorithm that takes some data as input and returns either &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-the-concept-behind-zkps&quot;&gt;Understanding the concept behind ZKPs&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The complexity of zero-knowledge proofs results in them typically being described with abstract examples, which elucidate the concept well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Suppose there is an underground cave with...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ZeroKnowledgeProof/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ZeroKnowledgeProof/</guid>
        
        <category>ZKP</category>
        
        <category>Cryptography</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organic Photovoltaics</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;organic-photovoltaics&quot;&gt;Organic Photovoltaics&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-&quot;&gt;Introduction :&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Photovoltaics is the process of directly converting sunlight into electricity without any heat engine to interfere. Photovoltaic devices are rugged and simple in design requiring very little maintenance and their biggest advantage being their construction as stand-alone systems to give outputs from microwatts to megawatts. Hence they are used for a vast array of applications resulting in the increase in demand for photovoltaics. Recently, ORGANIC PHOTOVOLTAICS (OPV), has been the subject of active research as this technology has the potential to spawn a new generation of low-cost, solar-powered products with thin and flexible form...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/organic-photovoltaics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/organic-photovoltaics/</guid>
        
        <category>Organic Photovoltaics</category>
        
        <category>Excitons</category>
        
        <category>Photo-active layer</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MEMS</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;mems-micro-electro-mechanical-systems&quot;&gt;MEMS (Micro Electro Mechanical Systems)&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;An introduction to field of micro systems and their applications.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“There is plenty of room at the bottom.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article deals with the emerging field of micro-electromechanical systems, or MEMS. MEMS is a process technology used to create tiny integrated devices or systems that combine mechanical and electrical components. These devices (or systems) can sense, control and actuate on the micro scale, and generate effects on the macro scale. MEMS has been identified as one of the most promising technologies for the 21st Century and has the potential...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/mems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/mems/</guid>
        
        <category>MEMS</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Demystifying Deconvolutions</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;demystifying-deconvolutions&quot;&gt;Demystifying Deconvolutions&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article mainly discusses about &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up-sampling with Deconvolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’ve heard about the term Deconvolution, and are willing to learn more about it, please read on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The contents of the this article is as follows:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The need for Up-sampling&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convolution Operation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Going backward&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convolution Matrix&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Transposed Convolution Matrix&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Deconvolution is also known as &lt;strong&gt;Transposed Convolution&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Fractionally-strided Convolution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-need-for-up-sampling&quot;&gt;The need for Up-sampling&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we use neural networks to process or generate images, there is a decrease in the size of the intermediate images in the subsequent layers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/deconv/p1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when an...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/deconv/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/deconv/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Convolution</category>
        
        <category>Up-sampling</category>
        
        <category>Neural Networks</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Supercapacitors</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A supercapacitor is a specially designed capacitor which has an enormous capacitance. While capacitors used in everyday life tend to have values in the nano or microfarad range, supercapacitors can have values of upto 12,000 F depending on their application.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/supercap/img1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;img1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;construction&quot;&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Like an ordinary capacitor, a supercapacitor has two plates that are separated. The plates are made from metal coated with a porous substance such as powdery, activated charcoal, which effectively gives them a bigger area for storing much more charge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What about the separator between the plates? In an ordinary capacitor, the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/supercap/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/supercap/</guid>
        
        <category>Supercapacitors</category>
        
        <category>Energy Storage</category>
        
        <category>Futurology</category>
        
        <category>Batteries</category>
        
        <category>Renewables</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
