<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:06:44 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:06:44 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evolution of bicycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolution of bicycle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ever since a person began thinking of sources of transportation, maximum development until date has been in the field of bicycle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the designs discussed briefly, innovation in them and the reasons for their failure or upgradation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first known bicycle was the &lt;strong&gt;velocipede&lt;/strong&gt;, a human powered vehicle which required the person riding it to actually push himself against the ground in order to move. No pedals, chain whatsoever, just 2 wheels, a frame and a seat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;media/e1074583fe8f083cc2b7e8326019e8f9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/8d/Draisine_or_Laufmaschine%2C_around_1820._Archetype_of_the_Bicycle._Pic_01.jpg/800px-Draisine_or_Laufmaschine%2C_around_1820._Archetype_of_the_Bicycle._Pic_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Slowly, came an era of multi-wheeled bicycles. Improved stability, increased load carrying...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Evolution-of-bicycle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Evolution-of-bicycle/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Should you really buy electric cars??</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Should you really buy an electric car?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Electric vehicles are hitting the world’s roads and with government support behind them these are hyped up to be the next big thing in the automobile industry . Combustion engine vehicles generate huge quantities of pollution, and developed economies create more than their fair share of this . The US transportation sector accounts for around 30 percent of US global warming emissions which is an order of magnitude more than most countries . In this blog I will tell you what I think on buying an electric car .&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First come the pros&lt;/p&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Electric-Cars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Electric-Cars/</guid>
        
        <category>Electric Cars</category>
        
        <category>CAS/SPS</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>t-SNE</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s manually impossible to understand the structure of a dataset with 100 dimensions. And it’s fairly common to come across data having so many features. And the exploratory-analysis of data is a preliminary step, before proceeding to other aspects of data-wrangling and models. This is where t-SNE comes in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-distributed_stochastic_neighbor_embedding&quot;&gt;t-SNE&lt;/a&gt; is non-linear dimensionality reduction algorithm. It reduces each high-dimensional point and embeds them into a 2D/3D map. Additionally, it ensures that similar objects are nearby and dissimilar points are kept apart.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internals of t-SNE: The math behind t-SNE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;There are two stages in the algorithm. First, it builds...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/tSNE/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/tSNE/</guid>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>t-SNE</category>
        
        <category>Data Visualization</category>
        
        
        <category>ML</category>
        
        <category>Data Visualization</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bit Manipulation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;All data in computer programs is internally stored as bits, i.e., as numbers 0 and 1. It turns out that there are many uses for bit manipulation in competitive programming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In programming, an n bit integer is internally stored as a binary number that consists of n bits. For example, the C++ type int is a 32-bit type, which means that every int number consists of 32 bits. For exmaple, the bit representation of the int number 42 is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;00000000000000000000000000101010&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several bit operations supported by a typical ALU, some of them being AND, OR, NOT, XOR, and...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 16:45:53 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bit-manipulation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bit-manipulation/</guid>
        
        <category>Bit masks</category>
        
        <category>DP</category>
        
        <category>Competitive Programming</category>
        
        <category>C++</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fluids and Satellites</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The increasingly large volumes of fluid that have to be carried aboard satellites designed for long operating lifetimes, but which often must also deliver high-accuracy pointing, mean that special attention has to be paid to the behavior of fluids in low gravity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;low-gravity-and-fluid-dynamics&quot;&gt;Low gravity and fluid dynamics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several methods for analyzing the dynamic behavior of fluids under normal gravity conditions on Earth. A common assumption in such methods is that the free surface of the fluid is flat and at right angles to the direction in which gravity is acting, i.e. normal to the gravity vector. In...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 16:35:53 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluids-and-satellites/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fluids-and-satellites/</guid>
        
        <category>Fluid Dynamics</category>
        
        <category>Satellites</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How is Technology Helping the Differently Abled People?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This year, the government of India dedicated the National Science Day to the theme “Science and Technology for specially-abled people”. The main aim was to encourage innovation and also to ease the difficulties of differently abled people. So here are 10 assistive technologies to assist them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;devices-for-people-with-visual-impairment&quot;&gt;Devices for people with visual Impairment&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;dot&quot;&gt;DOT&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is the world’s first Braille smart watch which is affordable compared to the regular e-Braille devices. Technically this device consists of 6 dots on four cells on the screen of the watch which forms 4 letters in Braille at any time. This tool helps...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 16:30:53 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-is-technology-helping-the-differently-abled-people/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-is-technology-helping-the-differently-abled-people/</guid>
        
        <category>differently-abled</category>
        
        <category>assistive technology</category>
        
        <category>text scanners</category>
        
        <category>optical sensors</category>
        
        <category>bionic</category>
        
        <category>eye tracking system.</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How do websites communicate securely?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The inherent need for human beings has always been to communicate and share information,albeit selectively. For this purpose, the information is to be coded in such a way that it can be deciphered only by the recipient, regardless of whether the recipient is right next to the sender or on the other side of the world. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The communication channel is assumed to be plagued with adversaries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.These adversaries have access to this coded information and are constantly trying to pry.So, the basic problem has always been to: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;transfer secure information over such insecure channels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, how DO you communicate when everyone...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 05:03:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/public-key-cryptography/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/public-key-cryptography/</guid>
        
        <category>SSL</category>
        
        <category>Public Key Cryptography</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>War of the Currents</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/War-of-the-currents/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;current&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Thomas Edison&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/War-of-the-currents/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;current&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Nikola Tesla&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the end of the 19th century, the world witnessed one of the greatest scientific feuds of all times, which changed the course of the history.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Three brilliant inventors, Thomas Edison, Nikola Tesla and George Westinghouse, battled over which electricity system—direct current (DC) or alternating current (AC)–would become standard. This would go on to be known as the ‘War of the Currents’.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By 1880, Edison had created a model for the incandescent lamp that was commercially viable. But to make a profit out of the electric lights that...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 05:03:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/war-of-the-currents/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/war-of-the-currents/</guid>
        
        <category>Tesla</category>
        
        <category>Edison</category>
        
        <category>AC/DC</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Speed Printing</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;3D printing technology is often used to construct highly complex objects of different kinds, properties and materials. Despite its numerous advantages, one major drawback of 3D printers is its traditionally slow speed. This is where it fails miserably, in its large scale applicability, against other major manufacturing processes like injection moulding. To overcome this major industry challenge, several 3D companies have come up with more updated and efficient technologies that guarantee quick speeds and utmost accuracy. One of the successful and modern technology is &lt;strong&gt;CLIP (short for, continuous liquid interface production)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;A typical 3D printing machine such...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 22:35:21 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/speed-printing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/speed-printing/</guid>
        
        <category>Speed Printing</category>
        
        <category>Stereolithography</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How NASA discovered planets using Artificial Intelligence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A Convolutional Neural Network.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;A Convolutional Neural Network and 90 minutes of training&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Clearly, the hard part wasn’t the training or the model but to get the &lt;em&gt;training set&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; But what is the &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt;? and where did we get it form?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2017 NASA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/artificial-intelligence-nasa-data-used-to-discover-eighth-planet-circling-distant-star&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; the discovery of an eigth planet in the &lt;em&gt;Kepler-90&lt;/em&gt; system. &lt;em&gt;Kepler-90&lt;/em&gt; is a Sun-like star 2545 light-years from Earth. The discovery was made using Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;where-did-the-data-come-from&quot;&gt;Where did the data come from?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;NASA has this huge camera up in space that has been sending us videos of...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 22:14:03 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/space-ml/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/space-ml/</guid>
        
        <category>Space</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
