<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 17:08:29 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 17:08:29 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Implementing Google Image Search Style Grid</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;implementing-google-image-search-style-grid&quot;&gt;Implementing Google Image Search Style Grid&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;I love design principles of Google. The way they present things is really awesome. One such presentation is Google Image Search.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/google_image_search/google_image_search.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Image Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Look at the way they arrange images. Each row has a fixed width, but their are no columns. The images have arranges themselves, intelligently, just enough to fit the row. I always wondered, what algorithm they must have used to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-thought&quot;&gt;What I thought&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;So my search began. Initially I thought they might have used some kind of knapsack algorithm to fit images to...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 17:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/google-image-search-grid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/google-image-search-grid/</guid>
        
        <category>Design</category>
        
        <category>Grid</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lighting Up your Room!</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;apparatus&quot;&gt;Apparatus:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;1.&lt;strong&gt;LED strips&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt; You should find these in most home decor stores. They could turn out to be expensive depending upon the quality of light you expect. There are RGB strips available too! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2.&lt;strong&gt;TIP 31 switch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Now this is a power transistor that can withstand large currents that the LED strips demand&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;3.&lt;strong&gt;AUX cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; This is to connect your music player to the device&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;4.&lt;strong&gt;12V battery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The LED strips demand a lot of current, so get one that supplies enough. There are rechargeable lead acid batteries available. They are cheaper, but bulkier...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 16:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/lighting-up-your-room/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/lighting-up-your-room/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
        <category>SPS</category>
        
        <category>EEE</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Class of NP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of us have this notion that NP stands for “Non Polynomial”, the problems which can’t be solved in polynomial time. This is not true. First of all, NP consist of only decision problem (given any problem, the answer should be yes or no) solvable in polynomial time by a theoretical non-deterministic Turing machine. Well, I am not going to cover non-deterministic Turing machine in this blog, so I will give another verifier based definition.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;verifier-based-definition&quot;&gt;Verifier Based Definition:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consider a decision problem X. Let I be an instance of X for which the answer is “yes”. Now if we...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2017 22:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-class-of-np/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-class-of-np/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Algorithms</category>
        
        <category>P v/s NP</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Not Chemical Engineering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what kind of fascination it is, probably parents sermon their little ones or the Indian school teachers are rather pedagogues, but this one notion of securing admission for undergraduation in a leading institute with specialisation in computer science is considered to be victory. I too was once a prey to this concept. The D-day shattered my dreams and landed me to choose one among the core branches. Hence, by elimination, the same technique one might use in the exams (xD), I chose chemical.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminary thoughts:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical engineering = Chemistry. Bury myself. Very disinclined to the idea of...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 12:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-not-chemical-engineering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-not-chemical-engineering/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Chemical</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to GPU Computing</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-gamers-priced-possession---graphic-cards&quot;&gt;A Gamer’s priced possession - Graphic Cards!&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s say that you have bought a brand new computer with one of the latest i7 processors but without installing a separate graphics card. And your friend is still using his 5 year PC with an old i3 processor, but with a high end graphics card installed. Both of you play the same game simultaneously on your own computers. But you notice that the gaming performance is better on his PC even though your computer is brand new. You scratch your head not understanding what’s going on here. You have a much...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-GPU-computing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-GPU-computing/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>High Performance Computing</category>
        
        <category>Game Development</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Get Started with Bots</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-get-started-with-bots&quot;&gt;How to get Started with bots&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have you ever been fascinated by robots - Awestrucking objects which are capable of performing some cool tasks without needing a human intervention (well, unless they decide to go mad! :P) ? And certainly the thought of how these genius creations work and can I make one too? must have crossed your mind. Being in a similar frame of mind couple of years back and having made some basic bots, I thought of writing this article to help the curious people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-stuff-together&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff together&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;It’s surely hard to shell out a few...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 23:58:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-to-get-started-with-bots/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-to-get-started-with-bots/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Bots</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-dissection-of-the-hello-world-c-program&quot;&gt;A dissection of the hello world C program&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;DISCLAMER: The contents on this page are strictly R rated. With R standing for Rigorous material. This is not a beginner’s guide to C. This is more of an article for intermediate/advanced users to explore C, in depth. I am not responsible for any earthquakes, alien invasions or epidemics caused, directly/indirectly from this material.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Given below is a typical C program taught in most of the textbooks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;codehilite&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt; // An include statement: Preprocessor Directive void main() // An entry function { printf(&quot;Hello world\n&quot;); } &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p&gt;The entire post...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 16:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Hello-World/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Hello-World/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>GCC</category>
        
        <category>C</category>
        
        <category>Programming</category>
        
        <category>HelloWorld</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting to love the Terminal</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-just-got-ubuntu&quot;&gt;I Just Got Ubuntu!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;But I’m not so sure about this command line&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Early days with the Unix command line interface, or the terminal (bash shell by default) can be pretty annoying and intimidating.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it doesn’t have to be. Getting to know the shell and writing shell scripts is exciting as well as extremely useful and something everyone should get familiar with. Once you get a hang of it you’ll start loving the flexibility Unix provides &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/456/&quot;&gt;in no time&lt;/a&gt;. But I wont go into too much details about shell scripting here, I’ll leave resources at the end...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 16:18:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/getting-to-love-the-terminal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/getting-to-love-the-terminal/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Unix</category>
        
        <category>Terminal</category>
        
        <category>Bash</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Installing Ubuntu For Windows Users</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;installing-ubuntu-for-windows-users&quot;&gt;Installing Ubuntu For Windows Users&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/installing_ubuntu/ubuntu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ubuntu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hie&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Installing Ubuntu on your machine is really helpfull in college days. It comes free and there are lots of open source softwares available for it. Last year, a lot of people came to my room for installing ubuntu on their machine. I once thought of opening shop for installing ubuntu (Just Kidding :P)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, this brief blog gives instructions on installing Ubuntu alongside Windows as a dual boot OS.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-a-partition-for-ubuntu&quot;&gt;1. Creating a partition for Ubuntu&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;First thing we need to do is create a partition to install ubuntu....</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 01:33:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/installing-ubuntu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/installing-ubuntu/</guid>
        
        <category>Linux</category>
        
        <category>Ubuntu</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice on Computer Science - Vinay Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/vinay-bhat-interview/vinay_bhat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vinay Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-do-you-think-should-be-done-in-college-to-enhance-your-resume&quot;&gt;Q. What do you think should be done in college to enhance your resume?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ans: One should Work hard to get a high GPA. An important aspect is to work on side projects as well-course projects or your own projects. Small projects help you understand and complete learning. It is ideal to contribute to Big Open Source repositories to understand big projects. Best thing is to try to leverage these projects into your first internship. It is more important to learn one language properly rather than every langauge and not master any one of...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/vinay-bhat-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/vinay-bhat-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
