<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 18:03:34 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 18:03:34 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do Generative Adversarial Nets matter?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A new class of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Models&lt;/strong&gt; was proposed in 2014 by &lt;strong&gt;Ian Goodfellow&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a The GANfather) which brought in a novel method of dealing with issues in ML and AI. The Invention of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/strong&gt; (GANs) can be regarded as one of the path-breaking innovations in making computers do useful stuff. GANs have seen some crazy development from an application perspective and has been one of the hottest topics for research in the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-does-a-generative-model-do&quot;&gt;So what does a Generative Model do?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main objective of a Generative Model is to create more samples of the &lt;strong&gt;same&lt;/strong&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Generative Adversarial Networks</category>
        
        <category>GANs</category>
        
        <category>Generative Models</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who doesn't want to live on another planet?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The colonization of Mars has been a popular theme of discussion over the past few decades. Whether it's in the spirit of exploration, expansion of human settlement or mining for additional resources, the idea of inhabiting another planet has allured us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is also evident in how often the idea of colonizing Mars appears in fiction and pop culture: from &quot;The Martian Chronicles&quot; by Ray Bradbury to &quot;The Martian&quot; by Andy Weir, the prospect of humans inhabiting the red planet has been explored from the perspectives of fantasy to science.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Keeping aside the political and ethical challenges that are intrinsic...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/colonization-of-mars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/colonization-of-mars/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bionics - The Gap between disability and ability</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.Bionics and its growing relevance&lt;/strong&gt; The rise of bionics has prompted some interesting questions- &lt;strong&gt;Can we trade away our biological body for a repairable one , one that won’t age?&lt;/strong&gt;. Bionics is defined as the science of connecting biological systems to artificial systems to develop machines that can imitate our biology. As bionic systems and transhuman augmentations exceed human capabilities humanity might soon face an interesting dichotomy - &lt;strong&gt;Either remain physically inferior and embody the cherished values of humanism&lt;/strong&gt; as we know them or to become a &lt;strong&gt;superior transhuman with a repairable body that can transcend the decay of aging&lt;/strong&gt;....</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</guid>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Generate Strange Text with GPT-2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;GPT-2 refers to a set of &lt;em&gt;Language Models&lt;/em&gt; released recently by OpenAI. My objective is to find weird ways that GPT-2 can fail, and also some smart things it is capable of. I’ll be using &lt;a href=&quot;https://talktotransformer.com/&quot;&gt;talktotransformer&lt;/a&gt; for this task. It’s a convenient tool that asks for a short text prompt, and then generates several lines of text to continue the prompt (no coding required!).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First, let’s see if you’re paying attention. Check out the following two samples:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Department of applied mechanics and hydraulics of National Institute of Technology - Karnataka (NIT-K), Suratkal will host a 3-day workshop on...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/generate-text-with-gpt2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/generate-text-with-gpt2/</guid>
        
        <category>NLP</category>
        
        <category>ML/AI</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Future of Drones</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;strong&gt;Drone&lt;/strong&gt; is used pretty often in today’s world. Today the term has broadened to include anything from highly sophisticated $100M Global Hawk to $30 teeny-tiny UDI 839 Quadcopter. Even flightless vehicle such as Drone ship are occasionally referred to as drones.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/FutureOfDrones/drones1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;​ &lt;strong&gt;Global Hawk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/FutureOfDrones/drones2.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;​ &lt;strong&gt;Quadcopter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So what exactly is a drone?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is called as an unmanned aerial vehicle essentially if it flies in a controlled way and their isn’t anybody on board. Whether it is controlled by computers or entirely controlled by a remote makes little difference. But...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/future-of-drones/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/future-of-drones/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concorde: Why did it fail?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Concorde: Why did it fail?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We had it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;From January 21st, 1976 to October 24, 2003, we had a commercial supersonic passenger service, called the Concorde, that would bring people from London to New York in just 3.5 hours, a journey that now takes about seven. Alongside the Tupolev Tu 144, Concorde was an aircraft that could brag about its supersonic speed, at a time when other jets could only manage speeds of about 800kmph.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over the years, Concorde came to represent class and style among the elite class in England, France and the United States. With tickets costing up...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/concorde/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/concorde/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forward Swept Wings</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Forward Sweeping is the concept of having the wings bent in the forward direction towards the fuselage (as seen in the picture of the X-29). Forward swept wings were first developed in the 1980s as an experiment to overcome many of the disadvantages of the rear sweep but little did we know what complications it would bring with it. To understand and evaluate the forward sweep we need to first understand why wings are swept back.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;x-29&quot;&gt;X-29:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/forward-swept-wings/x29.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;X-29&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A wing typically works on bernoulli’s principle where the air above the aerofoil has higher speed...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 01:00:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/forward-swept-wings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/forward-swept-wings/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Aeronautics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Space-based Solar Power</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Can you imagine deploying solar panels in space and efficiently converting the solar power that is received right from space and then transmitting the energy back to earth wirelessly, interesting right?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Space-based solar power&lt;/code&gt; project is a daring effort that collects the solar energy from the sun in space, converts it to energy and sends it down to Earth via microwaves. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Energy transmitting satellites&lt;/code&gt; that are placed in the geosynchronous orbit of the earth collect high intensity uninterrupted solar radiation by using giant mirrors that reflect huge amounts of solar rays onto two smaller solar...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:59:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/space-based-solar-power/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/space-based-solar-power/</guid>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Space</category>
        
        <category>Solar Power</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Password Security: Techniques and Challenges</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let me preface this article with something: There’s a very good chance that your password is not secure. In fact, if it’s anything less than nine characters long, any attacker could crack it in seconds if he had a decent GPU. Most of us know that ‘password’ is a very weak choice for a password, but there are some of us who think we’re smart and keep our passwords something like ‘p@$$w0r6’: It’s a terrible idea. Change it right now. ‘Hello123’ is probably safer than that. So what exactly is a safe password? And how do you even...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 14:50:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/password-security-techniques-and-challenges/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/password-security-techniques-and-challenges/</guid>
        
        <category>Systems</category>
        
        <category>Security</category>
        
        <category>Cryptography</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research, an informal testimony</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;research-an-informal-testimony&quot;&gt;Research, an informal testimony&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;The feeling of working with the author of textbooks that you first read to learn a subject is something beyond the ability of adjectives to explain. However, it is also the time when you begin to realize what you know is barely a fraction of what exists and that there’s always much more to learn. I am extremely privileged to have spent the summer at Stanford Microfluidics Lab as a UGVRI. Now before getting into more details I’d like you to know a little history and the following content is aimed at leaving you takeaway...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 17:00:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Requirements-and-Importance-of-Research/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Requirements-and-Importance-of-Research/</guid>
        
        <category>Requirements</category>
        
        <category>Research</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
