<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 22:01:35 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 22:01:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web Vulnerabilities</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;web-vulnerabilities&quot;&gt;Web Vulnerabilities&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;A vulnerability is a hole or a weakness in the application, which can be a design flaw or an implementation bug, that allows an attacker to cause harm to the stakeholders of an application. Websites across the world are programmed with different programming languages. Although each specific language have specific vulnerabilities ,issues exist fundamental to the internet that can show up disregarding the choosen language or framework used.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some Web Vulnerabilities&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;SQL Injection&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cross Site Request Forgery&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cross Site Scripting&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Server Side Request Forgery&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;sql-injection&quot;&gt;SQL INJECTION&lt;/h2&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-vulnerabilities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-vulnerabilities/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        <category>vulnerabilities</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PSLV to Mars</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;pslv-to-mars&quot;&gt;PSLV to Mars&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;mars-orbiter-mission&quot;&gt;(Mars Orbiter Mission)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Marking the series of events in the world history, November 5,2013 is recognized to be a day of great significance all over the world. On this day, ISRO launched MOM(Mars Orbiter Mission) also called Mangalyaan,a space probe orbiting Mars since September 24,2014.This made India the first Asian nation to reach Martian Orbit and the first nation in the world to do so in its first attempt.The launch took place from Satish Dhawan Space centre in Sriharikota.Indian scientists in ISRO proposed to launch the Mars satellite using PSLV(Polar Satellite Launch Vehicle) rocket. First,...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/pslv-to-mars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/pslv-to-mars/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>PSLV</category>
        
        <category>Mars</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Piezoelectricity and Piezoelectric Sensors</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;piezoelectricity-and-piezoelectric-sensors&quot;&gt;PIEZOELECTRICITY AND PIEZOELECTRIC SENSORS&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;piezoelectricity&quot;&gt;Piezoelectricity&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The accumulation of electric charge in solid materials in response to applied mechanical stress is called the piezoelectric effect or piezoelectricity, and those types of solid materials are called piezoelectric materials. Quartz, Berlinite (AlPO4), Sucrose (table sugar), Topaz, Tourmaline-group minerals, Lead titanate, etc. are some examples of naturally occurring piezoelectric materials. Some of the biological materials exhibiting piezoelectricity include silk, wood, enamel, tendon, etc. Barium titanate, Lead zirconate titanate, Potassium niobate, Sodium tungstate, Zinc oxide, etc., fall under the category of Synthetic ceramics that exhibit the piezoelectric effect. Piezoelectric effect is also exhibited...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/piezoelectricity-and-piezoelectric-sensors/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/piezoelectricity-and-piezoelectric-sensors/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Piezoelectricity</category>
        
        <category>Sensors</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Comprehensive Guide to Li-Fi</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/a-comprehensive-guide-to-lifi/1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Li-Fi Visual&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wouldn’t it be interesting if we could use our everyday LED bulbs as the transmitters of data for wirelessly accessing the internet, instead of Wi-Fi Routers or Cellular Networks? Li-Fi is a technology that does exactly that. Li-Fi was unveiled by &lt;em&gt;Dr. Harald Haas&lt;/em&gt; in his iconic 2011 TED Talk entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NaoSp4NpkGg&quot;&gt;Wireless data from every light bulb&lt;/a&gt;, where he demonstrated Li-Fi in public for the first time. Li-Fi (which is an acronym for &lt;strong&gt;Light Fidelity&lt;/strong&gt;), is a light-based communication system that is capable of transmitting data at high speeds over the visible,...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:01:55 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/A-Comprehensive-Guide-To-LiFi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/A-Comprehensive-Guide-To-LiFi/</guid>
        
        <category>Li-Fi</category>
        
        <category>Wireless Networks</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DS1: A demonstration spacecraft and its communication aspects</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;deep-space-1-how-and-what-does-it-do-on-space&quot;&gt;Deep Space 1: How and what does it do on Space??&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Deep Space 1 or DS1 is a satellite launched by National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) in 1998 to serve its purpose as a technology demonstration spacecraft. It was launched to test various upcoming technologies in space, its conditions, outcomes, threats or limitations of the proposed technology etc. in real time in space rather than earthly simulations. We are interested to learn how DS1 or any satellite in outer space carry out efficient communications to Space stations in Earth. For this, we must first be aware of Deep...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 12:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ds1-a-demonstration-spacecraft-and-its-communication-aspects/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/ds1-a-demonstration-spacecraft-and-its-communication-aspects/</guid>
        
        <category>RF transmission</category>
        
        <category>Antennas</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Autopilot</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;autopilots&quot;&gt;AUTOPILOTS&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;An autopilot is a flight control system that allows a pilot to fly an airplane without continuous hands-on control of the airplane. It allows the pilot to focus on higher-order tasks such as navigating, communicating with air traffic control, planning for weather contingencies and rerouting associated with any kind of emergency circumstance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/autopilot/Figure_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A simple autopilot combined with conventional navigation instruments.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;first-autopilots&quot;&gt;FIRST AUTOPILOTS&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the early days of aviation, pilots had to control the aircraft all the time to fly safely. As aircraft range increased and the flight durations increased, it became a serious problem...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 12:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/autopilot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/autopilot/</guid>
        
        <category>Autopilot</category>
        
        <category>Modern Aircraft</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stem Cell Technology</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;stem-cell-technology&quot;&gt;STEM CELL TECHNOLOGY&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-stem-cells&quot;&gt;What are stem cells?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Imagine waking up from a tragic accident that left you paralyzed from the neck down, will there be any hope to recover completely? Won’t it be amazing if there was a research that the use of stem cells could lead to potential treatments and cures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the advent of technology in the fields of artificial intelligence, robotics, genetics, etc., homo sapiens are finally at the threshold of a path to revitalizing and renewing our current fields of health care.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stem cells are cells that can differentiate into other types or kinds...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/stem_cells/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/stem_cells/</guid>
        
        <category>stem cells</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bluetooth Low Energy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We all know how infuriating it is when our devices drains battery when it uses wireless communication like wifi, bluetooth, infra-red. In every device we use, we are always concerned with the &lt;strong&gt;power consumption&lt;/strong&gt;. A device which consumes less power is always favourable. So in this article, I am going to elucidate an effective solution to the power problem in wireless communication- &lt;strong&gt;Bluetooth Low Energy&lt;/strong&gt; , also known as &lt;strong&gt;BLE&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;why-ble&quot;&gt;Why BLE?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Historically, &lt;strong&gt;classic bluetooth&lt;/strong&gt; (the bluetooth we are all aware of) was mainly designed to replace cable and it covers many protocols. And with speeds increasing with new...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Bluetooth-Low-Energy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Bluetooth-Low-Energy/</guid>
        
        <category>low power</category>
        
        <category>wireless communication</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Introduction To WebSockets</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have you ever wondered how the extremely volatile stock/share market prices are constantly updated on online portals?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;To have a glimpse of how rapid the changes are, head here&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptowat.ch/markets?types=spot%2Bfutures&quot; title=&quot;Cryptowatch&quot;&gt;Cryptowatch portal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Similarly how do new messages automatically pop up in Whatsapp Web or Facebook Chat?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-real-time-web-applications&quot;&gt;A Brief History of Real-Time Web Applications&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;When a user surfs the web, the browser (client) establishes a HTTP connection with a server; sends certain requests via RESTful routes (‘GET’, ‘PATCH’, ‘POST’, etc) to the server that hosts the website. The server receives the requests and sends information as responses...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/An-Intro-to-WebSockets/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/An-Intro-to-WebSockets/</guid>
        
        <category>Web</category>
        
        <category>Web Sockets</category>
        
        <category>Networks</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do Generative Adversarial Nets matter?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A new class of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Models&lt;/strong&gt; was proposed in 2014 by &lt;strong&gt;Ian Goodfellow&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a The GANfather) which brought in a novel method of dealing with issues in ML and AI. The Invention of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/strong&gt; (GANs) can be regarded as one of the path-breaking innovations in making computers do useful stuff. GANs have seen some crazy development from an application perspective and has been one of the hottest topics for research in the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-does-a-generative-model-do&quot;&gt;So what does a Generative Model do?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main objective of a Generative Model is to create more samples of the &lt;strong&gt;same&lt;/strong&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Generative Adversarial Networks</category>
        
        <category>GANs</category>
        
        <category>Generative Models</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
