<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 22:21:16 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 22:21:16 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coronary Stents</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-coronary-stents--work&quot;&gt;How coronary stents work?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Brief Breakdown On One Of The Most Frequented Surgeries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how exactly stents are used during or after an angioplasty? Why did this method replace bypass surgeries for minor heart attacks ? Well, read on to comprehend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-coronary-artery-disease-cad&quot;&gt;What is coronary artery disease (CAD)?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;CAD happens when a waxy substance called plaque builds up on the inner walls of the coronary arteries. This causes the arteries to harden and narrow, decreasing blood flow to the heart. As a result , the heart doesnt getthe blood, oxygen and nutrients it needs, which can lead...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:12:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/coronary-stents/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/coronary-stents/</guid>
        
        <category>heart</category>
        
        <category>disease</category>
        
        <category>treatment</category>
        
        <category>surgeries</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electronic Aspirin</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;electronic-aspirin&quot;&gt;ELECTRONIC ASPIRIN&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;For people who suffer from migraines, cluster headaches and other causes of chronic, excruciating head or facial pain, the &quot;take two aspirins and call me in the morning&quot; method is useless. Doctors have long associated the most severe, chronic forms of headache with the sphenopalatine ganglion (SPG), a facial nerve bundle, but haven't yet found a treatment that works on the SPG long-term.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, there is technology for the rescue: &lt;strong&gt;The Electronic Aspirin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is a patient-powered tool for blocking SPG signals at the first sign of a headache.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It consists of two components. A...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:03:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electronic-aspirin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/electronic-aspirin/</guid>
        
        <category>electronics</category>
        
        <category>neurostimulators</category>
        
        <category>remote control</category>
        
        <category>SPG</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web 3.0: The upcoming Web revolution</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-30-what-in-the-world-is-that&quot;&gt;Web 3.0?? What in the world is that???!!!&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a lot of buzz around web 3.0 and the changes it can bring in the world of tech. But only a few know what it actually is…Before hopping into web 3.0 let us know a little about its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Web 1.0&lt;/em&gt; , which started the whole damn internet and the &lt;em&gt;Web 2.0&lt;/em&gt; that we all use and love so much. Web 1.0 was just a set of &lt;em&gt;static websites&lt;/em&gt; . It comprised of a load of websites with no interactive information. But as the internet got faster and...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 03:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-3-0/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-3-0/</guid>
        
        <category>Web 3.0</category>
        
        <category>Ethereum</category>
        
        <category>Blockchains</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vortices</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;vortices&quot;&gt;Vortices&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;When everything seems to be going against you, remember that an airplane takes off against the wind, not with it&lt;/em&gt;” – Henry Ford&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article has been written especially for those who are interested in aerodynamics and also for people who are curious to know how small modifications in design help make an airplane or a car more aerodynamically efficient. The content is from an aerodynamic point of view, in an airflow.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/vortices/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fig.1&quot; title=&quot;Fig.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Vortex (Fig. 1) is nothing but a region in a fluid which revolves about a certain axis. These...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 02:50:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/vortices/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/vortices/</guid>
        
        <category>aerodynamics</category>
        
        <category>vortex</category>
        
        <category>formula 1</category>
        
        <category>aviation</category>
        
        <category>flight</category>
        
        <category>airflow</category>
        
        <category>fluids</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Light backscatter application</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;measure-of-fat-content-in-milk-with-led-and-ldr&quot;&gt;Measure of fat content in milk with LED and LDR&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India's milk production&lt;/strong&gt; is estimated to have increased by 6.6 per cent during the last four year. Price of milk is based on the quantity of FAT present in milk . so we need machine which can measures milk parameters like SNF (Solid but Not FAT), FAT, CLR, with less cost.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The important thing is that machine should be cheaper and only based on electricity .then it is very helpful for the remote area also.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming to the point photometric based sensor or light backscatter application technique is able...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 01:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/light-backscatter-application/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/light-backscatter-application/</guid>
        
        <category>light backscatter</category>
        
        <category>fat content in milk</category>
        
        <category>gerber method</category>
        
        <category>coagulating milk</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why 'you' need GPU</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-you-need-gpu&quot;&gt;Why you need GPU&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;You’ve probably wanted to buy a laptop/desktop with a GPU to play those awesome high graphics games that your friends keep talking about, and yes your parents wouldv’e probably said “You’re not going to get that. You need to study now”. But is that all the use there is for a GPU?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;gpu-vs-cpu&quot;&gt;GPU vs CPU&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah we all know what they stand for, so let’s skip that and get a little technical.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/why-you-need-gpu/cpuvsgpu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GPUvsCPU&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To put it in one line, we can say that if the CPU is being used for computations,...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-you-need-gpu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-you-need-gpu/</guid>
        
        <category>GPU</category>
        
        <category>parallel computing</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Varistor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Varistor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The name itself might have given you some idea about what it is, varistor stands for variable resistor&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is a varistor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Varistor is a varying resistor whose resistance depends on applied voltage,one of the special features of varistor is that it possesses non ohmic characteristics, which defines themselves as a non linear type of resistors&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It has two semiconductor elements fixed in a particular fashion (i.e. anti-parallel to each other) as to provide same characteristics for both directions of traversing current&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Its composition might have provided you with the insight that as it is made of semiconductor, it’s...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Varistor/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Varistor/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>resistors</category>
        
        <category>capacitors</category>
        
        <category>zener diode</category>
        
        <category>voltage transients</category>
        
        <category>regulators</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Automate The Industries</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;automate-the-industries&quot;&gt;Automate The Industries&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Industrial Automation refers to the use of sensors, robots , actuators in various industrial processes so that we get much better efficiency and the working labour required is low. Although the initial cost of setup of an automated industry is high, but the industrialists will surely be in profit if they apply the automation method as they can produce more no of goods in a limited time and also the quality of their products will increase as the human error in production is minimised.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are some of the industrial processes in which we can use...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Automate-The-Industries/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Automate-The-Industries/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Automation</category>
        
        <category>Industries</category>
        
        <category>Robots</category>
        
        <category>Manufacturing</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Machine Learning Matters ?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello everyone !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This article is for people who want a primer on &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/em&gt; and anyone who is curious about how Machines think.If you are already familiar with ML, this may not be the right place for you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;why-machine-learning-matters-&quot;&gt;Why Machine Learning matters ?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artificial intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; will shape our future more powerfully than any other innovation this century. The rate of acceleration is already astounding. After a couple of AI winters and periods of false hope over the past four decades, rapid advances in data storage and computer processing power have dramatically changed the game in recent years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 00:35:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Why-Machine-Learning-Matters/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Why-Machine-Learning-Matters/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Phase Change Material</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A Phase Change Material (PCM) is a substance with a high heat of fusion which, on melting and solidifying at a certain temperature, is capable of storing and releasing large amounts of energy. In the most basic terms, a PCM is a substance which can store and release large amounts of energy, typically in the form of heat. Although phase changes can occur among any combination of the three phases of a substance - gas, liquid, or solid - the most commercially viable transition is between the liquid and solid phases.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;working-of-a-pcm&quot;&gt;Working of a PCM&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A PCM in its’...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 02:05:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/phase-change-material/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/phase-change-material/</guid>
        
        <category>Storage Device</category>
        
        <category>Material</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
