<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 11:31:24 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 11:31:24 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why 50Hz ?</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-most-of-the-countries-use-a-5060-hz-110220-v-power-supply-and-not-any-othervalue&quot;&gt;Why do most of the countries use a 50/60 Hz, 110/220 V power supply and not any othervalue?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The answer to this question is not definite but quite a few technical and historical reasons can be found to support this which date back to the very beginning of the development of the electrical power system.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-supply-frequency-and-why-is-it-an-important-parameter-in-the-electrical-grid&quot;&gt;What is supply frequency and why is it an important parameter in the electrical grid?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/why-50hz/image001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The electrical power grid consists of a massive network of generators, transmission lines, transformers, substations and a variety of loads drawing real and reactive...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-50hz/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/why-50hz/</guid>
        
        <category>electric power grid</category>
        
        <category>50Hz frequency</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Market Basket Analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;market-basket-analysis&quot;&gt;Market Basket Analysis&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how Flipkart knows what items to suggest to you before and after you make a purchase? The is an aspect of analysis created specifically to promote sales called market basket analysis (MBA). In the retail industry, MBA refers to an unsupervised data mining technique that discovers co-occurrence relationships among customers’ purchase activities. The technique is based on the theory that if you buy a certain group of items, you are likely to buy another group of items. For example: while at McDonald’s, if you buy sandwiches and cookies, you are more likely to buy...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/market-basket/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/market-basket/</guid>
        
        <category>Data mining</category>
        
        <category>Apriori</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alterego</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;alterego&quot;&gt;AlterEgo&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;We basically can’t live without our cell phones, our digital devices. But at the moment, the use of those devices is very disruptive. Wouldn’t it be rather nice if we could just think of the question and a device could just Google it real quick and give the answer? Well, we’ve reached the point where robots can now read your mind. Kind of. Researchers at MIT have developed a wearable gadget that transcribes and responds to conversations users have with themselves in their heads. &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/alterego/alterego.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Comprised of a wearable device and a small computing system,...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/alterego/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/alterego/</guid>
        
        <category>Alterego</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envision Project 3: Regenerative Braking</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regenerative Braking&lt;/strong&gt; is an energy recovery mechanism which slows a vehicle or object by converting its kinetic energy into a form which can be either be used immediately or stored until needed. We have implemented this RBS in bicycles for generating electricity which can be used for different purposes like charging phones. For this we constructed a circuit to convert Mechanical energy to Electrical energy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/regenerative-braking/pic1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;pic1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;RBS is based on the principle of electromagnetic induction. On the application of brakes, the gears on the brakes come in contact with the rim of the...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/regenerative-braking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/regenerative-braking/</guid>
        
        <category>Braking</category>
        
        
        <category>Envision</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Washable Electronics using Water repellant Graphene Circuits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washable electronics? Water-repellent graphene circuits make it possible!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New graphene printing technology can produce electronic circuits that are low-cost, flexible, highly conductive and water repellent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/washable-electonics/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Landing image&quot; /&gt; The nanotechnology “would lend enormous value to self-cleaning wearable/washable electronics that are resistant to stains, or ice and biofilm formation,” according to a recent paper describing the discovery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;According to Jonathan Claussen, an Iowa State University assistant professor of mechanical engineering, an associate of the U.S. Department of Energy’s Ames Laboratory, they’re taking low-cost, inkjet-printed graphene and tuning it with a laser to make functional materials.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The research group used...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/washable-electronics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/washable-electronics/</guid>
        
        <category>graphene</category>
        
        <category>electronics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>QEMU/KVM for Virtual Machines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A “virtual machine” or “VM” is a virtual computer system. It is a tightly isolated software container with an operating system and application inside. Putting multiple VMs on a single computer enables several operating systems and applications to run on just one physical server, or “host.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A thin layer of software called a “hypervisor” decouples the virtual machines from the host and dynamically allocates computing resources to each virtual machine as needed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;qemu-and-kvm&quot;&gt;QEMU and KVM&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;QEMU or Quick Emulator is an open-source machine emulator and virtualizer. It can be used for full-system emulation, user-mode emulation as well...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/qemu-virtualization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/qemu-virtualization/</guid>
        
        <category>virtualization</category>
        
        <category>qemu</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Amazon Go - Cashier Less Shopping</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-amazon-go&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What exactly is Amazon Go?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Amazon Go is Amazon’s cashier-less shopping platform. Contrary to Amazon’s online website, the Go is a brick and mortar store- similar to your regular convenience store. What’s unique about the Go is that you can pick up an item and just walk out of the store without having to wait in line to pay for it. The store sells ordinary grocery items like bread, dairy and packaged ready to eat meals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/amazon-go/1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Landing image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A customer has to hold up a QR code on the Amazon Go...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/amazon-go/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/amazon-go/</guid>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        <category>spatial imaging</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS/SPS</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envision Project 2: Smart Lighting Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the ongoing developments in the technological World, a lot of efforts have been invested in the field of automation to make everyone’s life easier. As engineering students and the future of the World, it is our responsibility to lead the world into a better future via introducing technology which would reduce human effort as much as possible. Our project, &lt;strong&gt;Smart Lighting System&lt;/strong&gt; is aimed at automating the process of lighting of homes in order to personalize the control over the system and to adapt itself to its surroundings for better experience. So basically we decided to introduce...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-lighting-systems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-lighting-systems/</guid>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        
        <category>Envision</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envision Project 1 - Professor Matching for Research Internships</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finding research/internship opportunity under a professor’s guidance is exceedingly difficult because the professors are very busy and students are not well aware of the professors who are ready to give internship opportunities. The professor has to shortlist the resumes and the student has to find out and send a resume to every professor offering a research opportunity. Obviously, this is a time consuming and tiresome process for both students and the professors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We came up with a idea which not only speeds up this process but also makes it hassle-free. The idea is to create a platform which...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/prof-matching-envision/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/prof-matching-envision/</guid>
        
        <category>Android</category>
        
        <category>Web</category>
        
        <category>Django</category>
        
        
        <category>Envision</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evolution of bicycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since a person began thinking of sources of transportation, maximum development until date has been in the field of bicycle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the designs discussed briefly, innovation in them and the reasons for their failure or upgradation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first known bicycle was the &lt;strong&gt;velocipede&lt;/strong&gt;, a human powered vehicle which required the person riding it to actually push himself against the ground in order to move. No pedals, chain whatsoever, just 2 wheels, a frame and a seat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/cycle/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Archetype of a Bicycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Slowly, came an era of multi-wheeled bicycles. Improved stability, increased load carrying...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evolution-of-bicycle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evolution-of-bicycle/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
