<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 22:49:51 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 22:49:51 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Phase Change Material</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A Phase Change Material (PCM) is a substance with a high heat of fusion which, on melting and solidifying at a certain temperature, is capable of storing and releasing large amounts of energy. In the most basic terms, a PCM is a substance which can store and release large amounts of energy, typically in the form of heat. Although phase changes can occur among any combination of the three phases of a substance - gas, liquid, or solid - the most commercially viable transition is between the liquid and solid phases.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;working-of-a-pcm&quot;&gt;Working of a PCM&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A PCM in its’...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 02:05:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/phase-change-material/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/phase-change-material/</guid>
        
        <category>Storage Device</category>
        
        <category>Material</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Avionics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The merging of the words aviation and electronics, Avionics are all of the electronic devices and systems which perform individualized functions, used on any aircraft. Whether it is a military standard drone or a small hobby craft, it contains many electronic components which together achieve controlled flight. In this blog I’m going to talk mainly on the electronics aspect of the equipment used in small scale aircraft and drones.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;accelerometer&quot;&gt;Accelerometer&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/avionics/Accelerometer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Accelerometer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/avionics/AccelerometerIC.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Accelometer IC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An accelerometer is a transducer that is used to measure the physical or measurable acceleration that is made by an...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 19:57:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/avionics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/avionics/</guid>
        
        <category>Drone</category>
        
        <category>Hobbycraft</category>
        
        <category>Avionics</category>
        
        <category>Flight Control</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Segment Trees</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Segment trees are extensivly used in competitive programming for problems that invlove range queries and range updates.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, given an array A of N elements, answer Q queries (of two types):&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;1 L R : output the sum of elements between L and R&lt;br /&gt; 2 x I : A[I] = x&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A similar version of the above problem for minimum(i.e. to find the minimum between L and R) is famously known as Range Minimum Query. These problems can be easily solved with segment trees.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;naive-approach&quot;&gt;Naive Approach&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A naive approach would be to answer...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 04:25:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/segment-tree/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/segment-tree/</guid>
        
        <category>Competitive Programming</category>
        
        <category>Segment Trees</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nanoparticle-Wonder Liquid</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;magneto-serum---a-potential-panacea&quot;&gt;Magneto Serum - A potential panacea&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Though the name sounds very cool and straight out of a science-fiction franchise , what I’m referring to is actually called a ferro-fluid , but make no mistake , this liquid’s abilities are very near sci-fi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A ferro-fluid is basically a colloidal sol , made up of 3 components which are, nano-sized particles of a ferromagnetic substance like haematite or magnetite, a liquid dispersion medium and a surfactant ( citric acid for example) which prevents the nanoparticles from clumping together and depositing .&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What’s special about this fluid is that it gets strongly...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 05:00:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanoparticle-wonder-liquid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/nanoparticle-wonder-liquid/</guid>
        
        <category>nanotechnology</category>
        
        <category>nanomedicine</category>
        
        <category>magnetoserum</category>
        
        <category>panacea</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cloud Computing</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;You are probably using cloud computing right now, even if you don’t realise it. If you use an online service to send an email, edit documents, watch movies or TV, listen to music, play games or store pictures and other files, it is likely that cloud computing is making it all possible behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first cloud computing services are barely a decade old, but already a variety of organisations, from tiny start-ups to global corporations, government agencies to non-profits, are embracing the technology for all sorts of reasons.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-cloud-computing&quot;&gt;What is Cloud Computing?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/cloud-computing/Cloud_Comp.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cloud...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 05:00:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-computing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/cloud-computing/</guid>
        
        <category>Cloud Computing</category>
        
        <category>AWS</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Biomicry: Creating A Truly Sustainable Environment</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-something-that-is-common-between-the-bullet-train--self-cooling-houses--super-strong-adhesives-and-turbine-blades&quot;&gt;What is something that is common between the bullet train , self cooling houses , super strong adhesives and turbine blades?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well it turns out they are all inspired by nature is profound ways to optimise favourable characteristics and reduce unfavourable one. Yes! All these products have incorporated within themselves ideas inspired from nature to solve tricky problems in our world by a process called as biomimicry . Interested to know more about Biomimicry , stick on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-biomimicrybiomimetic&quot;&gt;What is biomimicry/biomimetic?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Biomimicry is a process in which systems , products , designs are modeled based on the /adapted from...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 22:00:33 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/biomicry-creating-a-truly-sustainable-environment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/biomicry-creating-a-truly-sustainable-environment/</guid>
        
        <category>Biomicry</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BIO(logy and electro)NICS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The living cell can be considered as an extraordinary piece of engineering, where each of the components of the cell work in precise coordination with utmost efficiency. Each cell generates its own energy which it uses to carry out specific tasks, and in the process, produces waste products which are removed from the cell. We are yet to understand the working of DNA and RNA, which are chains of particular bio molecules arranged in a certain order. This preprogrammed nature of life that allows for replication of molecular strands is what grabs the attention of many scientists today, and its...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:46:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</guid>
        
        <category>Biology</category>
        
        <category>Electronics</category>
        
        <category>Bionics</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>THE NEW BIOMETRIC - BRAINPRINT</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the conception of computers, mobile phones, tablets and most importantly, Internet, securing our devices and data has become crucial. Personal data ranging from shopping wishlists to bank details are either stored in PCs or are available online, all protected by passwords - a rather impotent sentinel, as it turns out. There have been several methods used by computers as well as the different websites to authenticate its user.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first passwords were simple and easily stored since sophisticated hacking networks did not exist yet. One such example is, Cryptographer Robert Morris, who created the infamous Morris worm, developed a...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:04:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/the-new-biometric-brainprint/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/the-new-biometric-brainprint/</guid>
        
        <category>biometrics</category>
        
        <category>brainprint</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proof-of-work as a consensus mechanism in blockchains</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: This article is not an introduction to blockchain, it does try to cover some basics of blockchain, but it’s focus is more on the proof-of-work as an approach to solving consensus problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;terminologies-and-breakdown&quot;&gt;Terminologies and breakdown&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The title of the article contains “consensus mechanisms in blockchain”, which sounds like a title with heavy words. So let’s try to first breakdown this title and understand each term separately.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus&lt;/strong&gt; : “Consensus” in simple terms means reaching an agreement amongst a set of parties about a specific thing like an event or a data value. Consensus is collaborative and...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 15:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/pow-consensus-blockchain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/pow-consensus-blockchain/</guid>
        
        <category>Blockchain, Consensus, Distributed systems</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quantum Supremacy: Is it hyped?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;quantum computer&lt;/strong&gt; has been buzzing around in recent years. But what is a quantum computer? Have they been built? How are they different from a classical computer? What kind of problems do they solve? Do I need to be an expert in physics to understand them?(Not really!). These may be some of the questions arising in your mind when you hear someone say “quantum computer”. In this article, I will address these questions by giving a basic understanding of quantum computer and what makes it so special.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;fundamentals&quot;&gt;Fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;All the electronic devices that we use in our...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 15:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/quantum-supremacy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/quantum-supremacy/</guid>
        
        <category>Quantum Computing</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
