<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 19:02:08 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 19:02:08 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stem Cell Technology</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;stem-cell-technology&quot;&gt;STEM CELL TECHNOLOGY&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-stem-cells&quot;&gt;What are stem cells?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Imagine waking up from a tragic accident that left you paralyzed from the neck down, will there be any hope to recover completely? Won’t it be amazing if there was a research that the use of stem cells could lead to potential treatments and cures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With the advent of technology in the fields of artificial intelligence, robotics, genetics, etc., homo sapiens are finally at the threshold of a path to revitalizing and renewing our current fields of health care.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stem cells are cells that can differentiate into other types or kinds...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/stem_cells/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/stem_cells/</guid>
        
        <category>stem cells</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bluetooth Low Energy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We all know how infuriating it is when our devices drains battery when it uses wireless communication like wifi, bluetooth, infra-red. In every device we use, we are always concerned with the &lt;strong&gt;power consumption&lt;/strong&gt;. A device which consumes less power is always favourable. So in this article, I am going to elucidate an effective solution to the power problem in wireless communication- &lt;strong&gt;Bluetooth Low Energy&lt;/strong&gt; , also known as &lt;strong&gt;BLE&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;why-ble&quot;&gt;Why BLE?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Historically, &lt;strong&gt;classic bluetooth&lt;/strong&gt; (the bluetooth we are all aware of) was mainly designed to replace cable and it covers many protocols. And with speeds increasing with new...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Bluetooth-Low-Energy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Bluetooth-Low-Energy/</guid>
        
        <category>low power</category>
        
        <category>wireless communication</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Introduction To WebSockets</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have you ever wondered how the extremely volatile stock/share market prices are constantly updated on online portals?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;To have a glimpse of how rapid the changes are, head here&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptowat.ch/markets?types=spot%2Bfutures&quot; title=&quot;Cryptowatch&quot;&gt;Cryptowatch portal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Similarly how do new messages automatically pop up in Whatsapp Web or Facebook Chat?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-real-time-web-applications&quot;&gt;A Brief History of Real-Time Web Applications&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;When a user surfs the web, the browser (client) establishes a HTTP connection with a server; sends certain requests via RESTful routes (‘GET’, ‘PATCH’, ‘POST’, etc) to the server that hosts the website. The server receives the requests and sends information as responses...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 07:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/An-Intro-to-WebSockets/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/An-Intro-to-WebSockets/</guid>
        
        <category>Web</category>
        
        <category>Web Sockets</category>
        
        <category>Networks</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do Generative Adversarial Nets matter?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A new class of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Models&lt;/strong&gt; was proposed in 2014 by &lt;strong&gt;Ian Goodfellow&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a The GANfather) which brought in a novel method of dealing with issues in ML and AI. The Invention of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/strong&gt; (GANs) can be regarded as one of the path-breaking innovations in making computers do useful stuff. GANs have seen some crazy development from an application perspective and has been one of the hottest topics for research in the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-does-a-generative-model-do&quot;&gt;So what does a Generative Model do?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main objective of a Generative Model is to create more samples of the &lt;strong&gt;same&lt;/strong&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/why-do-GANs-matter/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Generative Adversarial Networks</category>
        
        <category>GANs</category>
        
        <category>Generative Models</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who doesn't want to live on another planet?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The colonization of Mars has been a popular theme of discussion over the past few decades. Whether it's in the spirit of exploration, expansion of human settlement or mining for additional resources, the idea of inhabiting another planet has allured us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is also evident in how often the idea of colonizing Mars appears in fiction and pop culture: from &quot;The Martian Chronicles&quot; by Ray Bradbury to &quot;The Martian&quot; by Andy Weir, the prospect of humans inhabiting the red planet has been explored from the perspectives of fantasy to science.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Keeping aside the political and ethical challenges that are intrinsic...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/colonization-of-mars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/colonization-of-mars/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bionics - The Gap between disability and ability</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.Bionics and its growing relevance&lt;/strong&gt; The rise of bionics has prompted some interesting questions- &lt;strong&gt;Can we trade away our biological body for a repairable one , one that won’t age?&lt;/strong&gt;. Bionics is defined as the science of connecting biological systems to artificial systems to develop machines that can imitate our biology. As bionic systems and transhuman augmentations exceed human capabilities humanity might soon face an interesting dichotomy - &lt;strong&gt;Either remain physically inferior and embody the cherished values of humanism&lt;/strong&gt; as we know them or to become a &lt;strong&gt;superior transhuman with a repairable body that can transcend the decay of aging&lt;/strong&gt;....</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/bionics/</guid>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Generate Strange Text with GPT-2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;GPT-2 refers to a set of &lt;em&gt;Language Models&lt;/em&gt; released recently by OpenAI. My objective is to find weird ways that GPT-2 can fail, and also some smart things it is capable of. I’ll be using &lt;a href=&quot;https://talktotransformer.com/&quot;&gt;talktotransformer&lt;/a&gt; for this task. It’s a convenient tool that asks for a short text prompt, and then generates several lines of text to continue the prompt (no coding required!).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First, let’s see if you’re paying attention. Check out the following two samples:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Department of applied mechanics and hydraulics of National Institute of Technology - Karnataka (NIT-K), Suratkal will host a 3-day workshop on...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/generate-text-with-gpt2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/generate-text-with-gpt2/</guid>
        
        <category>NLP</category>
        
        <category>ML/AI</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Future of Drones</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;strong&gt;Drone&lt;/strong&gt; is used pretty often in today’s world. Today the term has broadened to include anything from highly sophisticated $100M Global Hawk to $30 teeny-tiny UDI 839 Quadcopter. Even flightless vehicle such as Drone ship are occasionally referred to as drones.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/FutureOfDrones/drones1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;​ &lt;strong&gt;Global Hawk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/FutureOfDrones/drones2.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;​ &lt;strong&gt;Quadcopter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So what exactly is a drone?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is called as an unmanned aerial vehicle essentially if it flies in a controlled way and their isn’t anybody on board. Whether it is controlled by computers or entirely controlled by a remote makes little difference. But...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/future-of-drones/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/future-of-drones/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concorde: Why did it fail?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Concorde: Why did it fail?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We had it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;From January 21st, 1976 to October 24, 2003, we had a commercial supersonic passenger service, called the Concorde, that would bring people from London to New York in just 3.5 hours, a journey that now takes about seven. Alongside the Tupolev Tu 144, Concorde was an aircraft that could brag about its supersonic speed, at a time when other jets could only manage speeds of about 800kmph.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over the years, Concorde came to represent class and style among the elite class in England, France and the United States. With tickets costing up...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 07:06:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/concorde/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/concorde/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forward Swept Wings</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Forward Sweeping is the concept of having the wings bent in the forward direction towards the fuselage (as seen in the picture of the X-29). Forward swept wings were first developed in the 1980s as an experiment to overcome many of the disadvantages of the rear sweep but little did we know what complications it would bring with it. To understand and evaluate the forward sweep we need to first understand why wings are swept back.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;x-29&quot;&gt;X-29:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/forward-swept-wings/x29.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;X-29&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A wing typically works on bernoulli’s principle where the air above the aerofoil has higher speed...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 01:00:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/forward-swept-wings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/forward-swept-wings/</guid>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Aeronautics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
