<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 15:16:13 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 15:16:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to big data and hadoop</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-big-data&quot;&gt;What is ‘Big data’?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;In simple terms, Big data is data which can’t comfortably be processed on a single machine. We live in a world increasingly driven by data. Try googling about big data and you will find some staggering facts like :&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The amount of data produced by us from the beginning of time till 2003 was 5 billion gigabytes. The same amount was created in every two days in 2011, and in every ten minutes in 2013 !!!&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;90% of the world’s data was generated in the last few years.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;A report from McKinsey &amp;amp; Co....</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/big-data/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/big-data/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Big Data</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>All about FinFETS</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello folks, today I’m going to discuss in detail about FinFET technology. The demand for smartphones and tablets with better performance and longer battery life has been driving the industry to come up with chips that are faster, smaller and use less power. To remain on this treadmill known as Moore’s Law, chipmakers have in recent years relied on a series of technological breakthroughs, most recently 3-D transistors known as FinFETs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The FinFET technology promises to provide the deliver superior levels of scalability needed to ensure that the current progress with increased levels of integration within integrated circuits...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/FinFETS/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/FinFETS/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>FinFETS</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fascinating world of Compliant Mechanisms</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-mechanism&quot;&gt;WHAT IS A MECHANISM?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;A mechanism is a mechanical device used to transfer or transform motion, force, or energy. Traditional rigid- body mechanisms consist of rigid links connected at movable joints. Whatever machines you see in your day to day life has some underlying mechanisms that govern its motion to produce the desired output. For example A NUT CRACKER works on the principle of MECHANICAL ADVANTAGE based on LEVER MECHANISM. This mechanism transfers energy from the input to the output. Since energy is conserved between the input and output (neglecting friction losses), the output force may be much larger...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Compliant-Mechanisms/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Compliant-Mechanisms/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Compliant mechanisms</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Peeking into a hacker's mind - an Interview with Kishor Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/kishor-bhat-interview/kishor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kishor Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As our world becomes increasingly networked, protecting these networks is no longer optional. A majority of today’s companies are insufficiently prepared for a cyber attack. Unfortunately, very few in NITK have cyber-security as their interest.I hope this interview with Kishor Bhat ,a cyber-security enthusiast motivates the readers into understanding the importance of cyber security in today’s digital world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;1-how-important-are-ctfs-to-a-security-enthusiast-give-an-account-of-your-experiences-from-playing-ctfs&quot;&gt;1. How important are CTFs to a security enthusiast? Give an account of your experiences from playing CTFs&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In my opinion, pretty important.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, CTFs or Capture the Flag contests are security competitions that...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/kishor-bhat-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/kishor-bhat-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Cyber Security</category>
        
        <category>CTFs</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A talk with - Abin Alex Pothen</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/abin-alex-interview/abin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abin Alex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;back-story&quot;&gt;Back-Story&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello guys, today I had a great opportunity to interview Abin Alex Pothen. He has done his BTech in Mechanical from NITK. He was an executive member of IEEE and SIGHT Chair in 2015. He is currently a Project Assistant at IISc and is working on non-linear control. With the amount of experience he possesses and the ‘air of intelligence’ he creates around the person he is interacting with, it was a great opportunity for me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-one-thing-you-want-mechanical-students-to-remember&quot;&gt;What is one thing you want mechanical students to remember?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;That question can be answered in...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/abin-alex-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/abin-alex-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Research</category>
        
        <category>Gyan</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dealing with Underdetermined Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://wikimedia.org/api/rest_v1/media/math/render/svg/ee0208dc07116e4d32bcc9952a015b43b63d91a2&quot; alt=&quot;incidence matrix&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-meant-by-under-constrained-system&quot;&gt;What is meant by “under-constrained” system?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I will start off this segment with my favourite quote.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“To the ones who tread the path less taken; To the ones who believe the answer to everything lies in data.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The answer to all problems lies in how much you know about it. Most engineering problems and their math models are inherently under-constrained. It is not surprising, we have all seen physics problems give under-constrained systems. The best example is in the definition of electric potential. All electric potentials are with reference to potentials at infinity where...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Dealing-with-underdetermined-systems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Dealing-with-underdetermined-systems/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>SPS</category>
        
        <category>Image Processing</category>
        
        <category>Linear Algebra</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hyperloop</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;hyperloop&quot;&gt;Hyperloop&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/hyperloop/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of the most valued and important entity nowadays is time. To help the people around the world to save their   travelling time, Elon Musk came up with an innovative idea of hyperloop. Hyperloop is a proposed mode of passenger and freight transportation that would propel a pod-like vehicle through a reduced-pressure tube that could potentially exceed airliner speeds. The pods would accelerate to cruising speed gradually using a linear electric motor and glide above their track using passive magnetic levitation or air bearings. The tubes could also go above ground on columns...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 06:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/hyperloop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/hyperloop/</guid>
        
        <category>hyperloop</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Graphene - A Wonder Material</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;graphene--a-wonder-material&quot;&gt;GRAPHENE – A WONDER MATERIAL&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;“I have never even heard of this term graphene before”, might be your thought process presently. Read further to understand why I call it a wonder material. What’s running in your mind at this point of time due to similarity in what you have studied is Graphite, an allotrope of Carbon which is very commonly found. But, what’s Graphene then? Yes, graphite and graphene are in fact the same except for a few structural differences which brings in unexpected properties. Graphite consists of various layers of Carbon atoms where each layer is arranged in...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2017 21:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/graphene/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/graphene/</guid>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Graphene</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Promises, Closures and Potatoes</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;promises-closures-and-potatoes&quot;&gt;Promises, Closures and Potatoes.&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well this article is mainly about Promises and Closures, two concepts that most of us don’t really care about in the beginning, but in reality, we have been using it a lot. “Promises and Closures” wouldn’t sound cool so I thought of slightly innovative title.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-are-promises&quot;&gt;So what are promises?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;They are not new, and they are pretty popular for a long time. &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/promises-closures-and-potatoes/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt; Promises gives you this feature of asynchronous nature in the code. It actually lets a third agent interact with your code: let’s take a small example. Assume that...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/promises-closures-and-potatoes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/promises-closures-and-potatoes/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>JavaScript</category>
        
        <category>Programming</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A talk with - Gaurav Hegde</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/gaurav_hegde_interview/Gaurav.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gaurav Hegde&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;back-story&quot;&gt;Back-Story&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello guys, I am Abijith, third year EEE. I had this opportunity among many opportunities to interview and talk to Gaurav. In my two years of IEEE and NITK life, I have been in touch with him for only one semester, because he took a semester off in his 7th semester. That semester has been the best academic semester for me. The discussions, the treats, the interactions, the projects, the amount of knowledge that this person has! Oh good lord!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anyway, without any further ado, presenting Gaurav. Note: Questions are in &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/gaurav-hegde-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/gaurav-hegde-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        <category>Math</category>
        
        <category>Gyan</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
