<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 22:03:37 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 22:03:37 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>EKRANOPLAN</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a closer look at the Ekranoplan &lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/EKRANOPLAN/ekranoplan_resize_md.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ekranoplan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Often referred to as the Caspian monster, the ekranoplan is one of the most freakish designs that were actually brought to life in a period where people were peaking at innovation in military hardware. It was designed to stay above the surface of water like a hovercraft but travel at far greater speeds like that of a commercial aeroplane. This was achieved with the help of an air cushion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hovercrafts have downward facing fans which generate the necessary lift while Ekranoplans used its wings and built up speed to...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 17:41:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/updatedekranoplan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/updatedekranoplan/</guid>
        
        <category>Ekranoplan</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Communication Protocols Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consider a multiplayer game that involves two or more participants. As there are many multiplayer games on an online platform, there’s always a need to be a proper collaboration between the players. A game is only as good as its rules, and how well we play the game is defined by how well we follow the rules. Often, players ignore these “protocols” and end up messing the system with no result and just chaos. From this, you may guess these “protocols” are not just a necessity in games, but most of the aspects of life. Users (which include...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 17:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/communication-protocols-part1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/communication-protocols-part1/</guid>
        
        <category>Communication</category>
        
        <category>Protocols</category>
        
        <category>Synchronous</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Dive into Git Directory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Git is a distributed version control system. It means Git helps you manage different versions of your work, record the changes and helps different collaborators work parallelly on the same project.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Imagine that you are working on a big project involving many files and folders in it. You make a series of changes to your project and now finally when you compile it, you see the application is crashing or not working as expected. In such a case, Git is the best tool you could use. If you have recorded all your changes uniformly in Git, you can any time...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 15:40:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/a-dive-into-git-directory/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/a-dive-into-git-directory/</guid>
        
        <category>Git</category>
        
        <category>Github</category>
        
        <category>Bash</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Genome Editing</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;genome-editing&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GENOME EDITING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A genome is an organism’s complete set of DNAs, together with all of its genes. Every genome contains all the data required to create and maintain that organism.&lt;/em&gt; In humans, a replica of the whole genome (more than three billion DNA base pairs) is contained in all cells that have a nucleus. Modification to provide desired traits in plants, animals, and microbes used for food began around 10,000 years ago. These changes, in conjunction with natural evolutionary changes, have resulted in common food species that are currently genetically totally different from their ancestors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog_src/assets/img/Genome-Editing/figure1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Genome Editing&quot;...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Genome-Editing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Genome-Editing/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Genome Editing</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Application of Neural Networks in Power Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;application-of-neural-networks-in-power-systems&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application of Neural Networks in Power Systems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard of Machine Learning or Neural Networks, but you don’t know their applications? Scroll down to find out!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For most beginners, the title itself might be a bit complicated to digest. So let’s split it into its 2 major components - &lt;strong&gt;Neural Networks&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Power Systems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-neural-networks&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are Neural Networks?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neural networks are a set of algorithms, modeled after the human brain, primarily designed to recognize patterns. To understand how a neural network works, one must know the related terminologies. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/What-is-Machine-Learning/&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a blog that contains the...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Applications-of-Neural-Networks-in-Power-Systems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Applications-of-Neural-Networks-in-Power-Systems/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Power Systems</category>
        
        <category>Neural Networks</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is machine learning?</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-machine-learning&quot;&gt;What is Machine Learning?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Machine learning is a school of computer science that focuses on programming machines to improve their performance through data and iteration. The machine can learn without being explicitly programmed. Yes, you read it right. This is called Artificial intelligence, where we feed in data into the machine, and it learns the data and predicts the output for any other input given. Machine learning is broadly classified into&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Supervised Learning In supervised learning, we have an idea of the relationship between the inputs and the outputs from the dataset given. It is further classified into...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/What-is-Machine-Learning/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/What-is-Machine-Learning/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Overview of Tarjan's Algorithm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Strong components in directed graphs are components in which all vertices are strongly connected to each other. 2 vertices A and B are strongly connected if there is a directed path from A-&amp;gt;B and B-&amp;gt;A.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need for Computing Strongly Connected Components&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Computing strong components for graphs has been a need in computation since many years now. Biologists use the strong components to find out sub-ecosystems in a food chain. During the early advent of the internet, this became an absolute necessity as dependency graphs of various software modules needed to be processed and their strong components extracted,...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/TarjansAlgo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/TarjansAlgo/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SLAM Coverage Algorithms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MX2qcDM11N4&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/MX2qcDM11N4/hqdefault.jpg?sqp=-oaymwEZCNACELwBSFXyq4qpAwsIARUAAIhCGAFwAQ==\u0026rs=AOn4CLADHXP3O1dRP2zZkPvkSwY2-fFvyQ&quot; alt=&quot;Image Link to Video&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; With the increased use of robots in industries, the need for robots to be more efficient is incredibly high. One of the key concerns is the way in which they commute. Gone are the days when robots were restricted to moving in a pre-defined path, and one of the most fundamental technologies for locomotion of mobile robots are coverage algorithms. Coverage algorithms require that they allow the bot to cover the maximum area possible without any human intervention. In previously used algorithms, the coverage was achieved with robots crossing the entire length...</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/SLAM/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/SLAM/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Solving a traffic problem using graph decomposition</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;solving-a-traffic-problem-using-graph-decomposition&quot;&gt;Solving a traffic problem using graph decomposition&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Capital city&lt;/strong&gt; is known for its prosperous life and big opportunities. Its inhabitants are called &lt;em&gt;“capitolates”&lt;/em&gt;. Every capitolate in Capital city wants to live a happy and peaceful life. Now Capital city has three divisions - Residential town, Fun town and &lt;strong&gt;market city&lt;/strong&gt;. Residential town is where capitolates live. Fun town is where they meet friends and make merry. Market city is where they work to make a living. But every passing year, capitolates are becoming more and more frustrated and unhappy. The reason is that people from neighbouring lands want...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 17:51:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Solving-a-traffic-problem-using-graph-decomposition/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/Solving-a-traffic-problem-using-graph-decomposition/</guid>
        
        <category>Algorithms</category>
        
        <category>Graph Theory</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web Vulnerabilities</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;web-vulnerabilities&quot;&gt;Web Vulnerabilities&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;A vulnerability is a hole or a weakness in the application, which can be a design flaw or an implementation bug, that allows an attacker to cause harm to the stakeholders of an application. Websites across the world are programmed with different programming languages. Although each specific language have specific vulnerabilities ,issues exist fundamental to the internet that can show up disregarding the choosen language or framework used.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some Web Vulnerabilities&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;SQL Injection&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cross Site Request Forgery&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cross Site Scripting&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt; &lt;p&gt;Server Side Request Forgery&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;sql-injection&quot;&gt;SQL INJECTION&lt;/h2&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-vulnerabilities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieee.nitk.ac.in/blog/web-vulnerabilities/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        <category>vulnerabilities</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
