<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 12:17:07 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 12:17:07 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Brain behind a Formula One Car</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The track belongs to the driver, the pits belong to the engineers&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Formula One cars are mean machines. They have been fine tuned for one purpose- Speed. In fact, they are the most efficient mode of transport after space shuttles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Be it aerodynamic performance, super-efficient engines or state of the art tyre management strategies, engineers have scaled new heights in their pursuit for speed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ecu&quot;&gt;The ECU:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, one aspect of the car that goes largely unnoticed is the electrical system. If the chassis and the engine form the arms and legs, &lt;strong&gt;the Electronic Control Unit&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;the...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/The-Brain-behind-a-Formula-One-car/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/The-Brain-behind-a-Formula-One-car/</guid>
        
        <category>Formula One</category>
        
        <category>ECU</category>
        
        <category>TAG-320</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Robots Can Now See In 3D</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Autonomous robots can inspect nuclear power plants, clean up oil spills in the ocean, accompany fighter planes into combat and explore the surface of Mars.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet for all their talents, robots still can’t make a cup of tea.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That’s because tasks such as turning the stove on, fetching the kettle and finding the milk and sugar require perceptual abilities that, for most machines, are still a fantasy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Among them is the ability to make sense of 3-D objects. While it’s relatively straightforward for robots to “see” objects with cameras and other sensors, interpreting what they see, from a single glimpse,...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Robots-can-see-in-3d/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Robots-can-see-in-3d/</guid>
        
        <category>Robots</category>
        
        <category>Computer Vision</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Generative Adversarial Networks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last 2 years, &lt;strong&gt;Generative Models&lt;/strong&gt; have been one of the most active areas of research in the field of Deep Learning. The paper on &lt;strong&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a GANs) published by &lt;strong&gt;Ian Goodfellow&lt;/strong&gt; in 2014 triggered a new wave of research in the field of Generative Models. Today we’ll explore what makes GANs so different and interesting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/GAN/ideal-gen-model.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ideal Generative Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main objective of a Generative Model is to learn the &lt;em&gt;probability distribution&lt;/em&gt; from which the training data is sampled. Once the model learns the probability distribution, it can sample new data from...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Generative-Adversarial-Networks/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Generative-Adversarial-Networks/</guid>
        
        <category>Deep Learning</category>
        
        <category>Generative Adversarial Networks</category>
        
        <category>GANs</category>
        
        <category>Generative Models</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Search Engine Optimisation</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Guess how many websites come up each day.&lt;br /&gt; Any ideas?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;A survey by Netcraft in 2012 showed that total number of websites launched in 2012 were &lt;em&gt;51 million&lt;/em&gt; i.e. ~140,000 per day.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This flood makes it necessary for your website to stand out from the rest. But , how can this be done ?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;strong&gt;SEO i.e. Search Engine Optimisation&lt;/strong&gt; comes into play.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/SEO/gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;SEO and Ranking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a world where &lt;strong&gt;over 90% of online experiences start with a search engine,&lt;/strong&gt; showing up on the front page of Google Search can...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 10:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Search-Engine-Optimisation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Search-Engine-Optimisation/</guid>
        
        <category>SEO</category>
        
        <category>Google</category>
        
        <category>Web</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Raspberry Pi Tutorial</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have just started exploring microcontrollers and experimenting with development boards like Arduino and Raspberry Pi, you might have had struggles with configuring the board and interfacing them with the hardware that you used to build your little fascinating circuits. I too, faced some issues when I had to set up my Raspberry Pi B+ model.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Most of the instructables available online give instructions for working with a separate monitor connected to RPi using a HDMI cable. However, to make things convenient, you can use your laptop display itself to work with your Rpi. This requires a few additional...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/RPi-tutorial/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/RPi-tutorial/</guid>
        
        <category>Raspberry Pi</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aircraft Engines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you might have flown in an aircraft at least once in your lifetime and even if you haven’t, you might have at least seen one in a picture. You might have noticed that there are different types of aircraft for different purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some are small and can accommodate only 5 people while some are huge and can carry more than 600 people, some are used for dropping bombs while some others are used for rescuing people during disasters.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of the most essential parts of any of these aircrafts is the engine. The engine provides the thrust required...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 10:25:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Aircraft-Engines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/Aircraft-Engines/</guid>
        
        <category>Aircraft Engines</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fingerprint Recognition</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Fingerprint recognition systems are practically everywhere today, from your smartphone, laptops, and are an integral part of the Aadhar system enabling us to authenticate our identity easily. Here’s a look at how the whole system of fingerprint recognition works.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fingerprints are the tiny friction ridges on the ends of our fingers and thumbs make it easier to grip things. By making our fingers rougher, these ridges increase the force of friction between our hands and the objects we hold, making it harder to drop things. Unless you have accidents with your hands, your fingerprints remain the same throughout your life.&lt;/p&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 03:05:05 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fingerprint-recognition/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/fingerprint-recognition/</guid>
        
        <category>fingerprint</category>
        
        <category>sensors</category>
        
        <category>fingerprint sensor</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Intriguing World of Chatbots</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;﻿&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;“Hey Siri, What’s my schedule for today”&lt;br /&gt; “Hey Cortana, when is my appointment with the dentist today”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;These are a few phrases that we use casually from day to day in order to make our life a tad bit easier. In this time of rapid advances in AI and Machine learning Chatbots are one avenue that has been ushered into reality by this magical paradigm that has been growing by leaps and bounds in the past few years. But what if Chatbots can be a vital link in another field that is rapidly gaining traction, namely...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 03:03:05 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/chatbot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/chatbot/</guid>
        
        <category>Chatbot</category>
        
        <category>Chat</category>
        
        <category>Bots</category>
        
        <category>Language Processing</category>
        
        <category>IoT</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Biohacking</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;﻿Ever fantasied becoming the Cyborg from DC comics universe? Well, brace yourself, because that dream is soon to come into reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Introducing Biohacking, a fairly new practice that could bring major changes in human life as we know it. Biohacking can be defined as a “social movement involving studying basic biology and exploiting it to make electronic implants made using easily available equipment”. In short, you make a cyborg out of yourself. As “punk” as it sounds, this practice caught the attention of media because of the possibilities it opens.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/biohacking/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;RFID chip&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ron Shigeta&lt;/strong&gt; runs Berkeley Biolabs,...</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 02:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/biohacking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/biohacking/</guid>
        
        <category>biology</category>
        
        <category>hacking</category>
        
        <category>biological hacking</category>
        
        <category>superhuman</category>
        
        <category>cyborgs</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quantum Computers and The Future of Computation</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Quantum Mechanics a realm of physics where the tiny subatomic particles reside and whose physics is beyond the perception of the classical physical world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;1-what-makes-this-realm-so-weird-and-different-in-working&quot;&gt;1] What makes this realm so weird and different in working?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;The behaviour working of these particles was resolved by proposing of a mathematical model governed by the principle of Superposition, entanglement and tunnelling.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Quantum Computers makes use of these physical phenomena to do it calculation and this is where the speciality of the futuristic computing machines lies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/quantum-computers/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;quantum computer&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;The first ever made quantum computer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;breaking-the-myth-of-superposition-theorem&quot;&gt;Breaking The Myth...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2017 15:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/quantum-computers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/quantum-computers/</guid>
        
        <category>Quantum Computing</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
