<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 16:07:35 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 16:07:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Radio-frequency Identification:</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;radio-frequency-identification&quot;&gt;RADIO-FREQUENCY IDENTIFICATION&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;RFID technology has been in circulation for many years now. You may have encountered it first-hand while borrowing library books, or while swiping for attendance in school. Recently, the government issued RFID chips to be installed in cars so that we can zoom through toll booths instead of waiting in long queues. RFID technology has also got a fair share of screen time. Remember Casino Royale? Her Majesty’s Secret Service injects Bond with a glass-enclosed, rice-sized RFID chip, so that, in M’s words, “they’ll know where he is”. Here is a little insight into the technology that is taking...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 21:08:32 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/rfid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/rfid/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Smart Grid</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;How many times have you felt guilty about excessive usage of electricity when you see your monthly bill? Imagine managing the electricity delivered to your house like you manage activities like personal banking from a computer!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You will no longer have to wait till the end of the month to know how many units you have consumed- you have “Smart meters,” and other mechanisms, will allow you to see how much electricity you use, when you use it, and its cost. It also comes with real-time pricing, which will allow you to save money by using less power...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-grid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-grid/</guid>
        
        <category>Ice</category>
        
        <category>Fluid Dynamics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magnetically Repelling Ice</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;People can be nervous fliers to begin with. Even when there isn’t a cloud in the sky, there are few words that cause anxiety in some like, “Prepare for takeoff.” But add wintry conditions to the mix, add some ice, and the uneasy feeling can turn to fear.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-ice-cause-a-plane-to-crash&quot;&gt;How does ice cause a plane to crash?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ice typically builds up when tiny cloud droplets impact and freeze on the leading edges, or front surfaces, of the plane. The ice alters airflow over the wing and tail, reducing the lift force that keeps the plane in the air, and potentially...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/magnetically-repelling-ice/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/magnetically-repelling-ice/</guid>
        
        <category>Ice</category>
        
        <category>Fluid Dynamics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Beginning Of The End - Have The Machines Won?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wondering when artificially intelligent robots will take over the Earth? Wonder no more — they’ve already done it! You’re probably thinking&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;But wait. Wouldn’t I have noticed if chrome-plated autonomous killing machines began to exterminate humans? Not necessarily.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;It turns out evil robots in cyber-space are nowhere near as flashy as their science-fiction counterparts. We envisioned Cylons, Terminators, and Cyborgs but failed to imagine the much more immediate threat of helpful neural-network learning algorithms. I’m talking about Alexa, Echo, Siri, Google Home, the Internet of Things, even social networking platforms masquerading as news sources. They control content. They learn...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-beginning-of-the-end-have-the-machines-won/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-beginning-of-the-end-have-the-machines-won/</guid>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        <category>AI threat</category>
        
        
        <category>Compsoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Docker</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Docker is probably the most talked-about infrastructure technology of the past few years. And why not? It makes managing and deploying applications so much easier without the overhead of a Virtual Machine. Here’s how:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; is a tool designed to make it easier to create, deploy, and run applications by using containers. &lt;strong&gt;Containers&lt;/strong&gt; allow a developer to package up an application with all of the parts it needs, such as libraries and other dependencies, and ship it all out as one package. By doing so, thanks to the container the developer can rest assured that the application will run on...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 15:40:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-docker/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/introduction-to-docker/</guid>
        
        <category>Docker</category>
        
        <category>Containers</category>
        
        <category>DevOps</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The LIGO Experiment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The LIGO (Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory) Experiment – A completely different perspective of studying the universe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;einsteins-prediction&quot;&gt;Einstein’s Prediction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/the-ligo-experiment/image1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Einstein’s Prediction&quot; height=&quot;294px&quot; width=&quot;270px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over a century ago, Albert Einstein proposed the idea of something called a Gravitational Wave which was a part of his General Theory of Relativity. The concept of Gravitational waves suggests that, the force of gravity is not an actual force but rather, a distortion in the fabric of spacetime. This was just an idea, as there was no experimental evidence to support Einstein’s claim.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-gravitational-wave&quot;&gt;What is a gravitational wave?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A gravitational wave...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 15:40:09 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-ligo-experiment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-ligo-experiment/</guid>
        
        <category>LIGO</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wireless Power Transmission</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We cannot imagine the world without electric power. Generally power is transmitted through wires, however there is an idea to eradicate the hazardous usage of electrical wires which involves a lot of confusion particularly in organizing them. Some of these devices might not even need their bulky batteries to operate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are the techniques of transmitting power without using wires with an efficiency of about 95% with non-radiative methods, due to which it does not affect the environment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In any system of coupled resonators there often exists a so-called “strongly coupled” regime of operation. If one ensures to operate in...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 15:40:08 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/wireless-power-transmission/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/wireless-power-transmission/</guid>
        
        <category>Power</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Iot communications easy using mDNS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A project in Iot often requires multiple devices communicating with each other. This is usually done through sending messages over sockets. To locate a device, usually addresses are used. This is good technique, but due to commom use of DHCP, the IP addresses change constantly. So one needs to keep track of these changing IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What if you don’t need to remember the changing IP addresses? That’s where mDNS comes into picture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-mdns&quot;&gt;What is mDNS?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multicast_DNS&quot;&gt;mDNS&lt;/a&gt; stands for Multicast Domain Name System. Apple needed to use readable machine names on a local network without a nameserver, so...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/using-mdns-in-iot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/using-mdns-in-iot/</guid>
        
        <category>Iot</category>
        
        <category>Networking</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Honeycomb Conjecture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do bees build &lt;strong&gt;hexagonal structured&lt;/strong&gt; hives? Why not any other shape? Let us deliberate these questions which troubled many thinkers. &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/the-honeycomb-conjecture/img1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consider prisms of different regular polygons and assume them to have same height and volume. This means that the one with the &lt;strong&gt;least&lt;/strong&gt; perimeter will require the least material to build. We know that as we increase number of sides in the polygon, perimeter decreases. So, cylinder will use the least amount of material (circle can be considered as a polygon with infinite sides).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But cylinders are economical only if they stand alone. If placed...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 19:21:02 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-honeycomb-conjecture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-honeycomb-conjecture/</guid>
        
        <category>Honeycomb Conjecture</category>
        
        <category>Hexagonal cells</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charge your phone whenever you walk into the room</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;charge-your-phone-whenever-you-walk-into-the-room&quot;&gt;CHARGE YOUR PHONE WHENEVER YOU WALK INTO THE ROOM&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;One quick and easy way to induce anxiety is to misplace your phone charger. You’re stressed out just thinking about it right now, well what if instead of dealing with your wiry bundles and ports and mats and plugs and cords, you could just….walk into a room and automatically your mobile phones, laptops any other appliances get charged. However, mobile devices are not truly mobile if they require connection to power cord.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wi-charge technology provides us finally a way to get rid of the power cord, efficiently and safely. The...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 19:21:02 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/charge-your-phone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/charge-your-phone/</guid>
        
        <category>transmitter</category>
        
        <category>reciever</category>
        
        
        <category>CAS</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
