<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>A blog documenting random findings and musings of our members</description>
    <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ieeenitk.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 18:29:54 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 18:29:54 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Airbag System for two Wheeler vehicles</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Airbag system was first introduced in 4-wheelers . This paper gives information about the introduction of the airbag system can be used in the two wheelers(bikes). This paper shows the working, construction, installation of this system and problems that can occur in this system.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The concept of this airbag system is “To reduce the injuries to a rider when impacting with an opposing vehicle and/or opposing object in frontal collisions by absorbing rider kinetic energy and by reducing rider separation velocity from motorcycle in the forward direction.” With the help of the ANGLE sensor with an angle...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 07:30:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-airbag-system-for-two-wheeler-vehicle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-airbag-system-for-two-wheeler-vehicle/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BoT</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;botnet-of-things&quot;&gt;Botnet of things&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Internet of Things aka IoT is one of the hot trending topics in the tech world right now. The IoT is basically a network of devices connected to the internet, each having a unique IP address. Today, the Internet of Things plays with the idea of connecting nearly every manufactured object to the Internet. It is being incorporated into smart homes, watches, cars, fitness trackers, power grids, thermostats, contact lenses, pacemakers and what not.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While the Internet of Things brings a new horizon of opportunities, there are several barriers in respect to making IoT implementations...</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 07:30:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bot/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/bot/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A step ahead in Reverse Engineering!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello to all the computer enthusiasts out there!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this article,we will look into a simple C program intended to perform a particular task is MADE to perform a task it was not supposed to perform. SO,WE WILL BE TRYING TO FOOL THE COMPUTER!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id=&quot;pre-requisites-&quot;&gt;Pre-requisites :&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;A computer which runs Linux.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;A curious mind which wants to know how stuff actually works!&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt; &lt;p&gt;We will be using GDB(GNU Debugger) to understand the C program at the assembly level.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If GDB is not installed in your box,you can type in this command to install it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo...</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 07:30:10 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/a-step-ahead-in-reverse-engineering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/a-step-ahead-in-reverse-engineering/</guid>
        
        <category>CTF</category>
        
        <category>Ethical Hacking</category>
        
        <category>Security</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Radio Frequency Identification</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;RFID technology has been in circulation for many years now. You may have encountered it first-hand while borrowing library books, or while swiping for attendance in school. Recently, the government issued RFID chips to be installed in cars so that we can zoom through toll booths instead of waiting in long queues. RFID technology has also got a fair share of screen time. Remember Casino Royale? Her Majesty’s Secret Service injects Bond with a glass-enclosed, rice-sized RFID chip, so that, in M’s words, “they’ll know where he is”. Here is a little insight into the technology that is taking the world by...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 06:00:02 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/rfid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/rfid/</guid>
        
        <category>RFID</category>
        
        <category>ADC</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Machine Learning for Stock Market Investment</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Arthur Lee Samuel, the man who coined the term “machine learning” defined it as the field of study that gives computers the ability to learn without being explicitly programmed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;A good analogy to how it actually works would be teaching a child to play chess by locking him in a room with nothing but the rules of the game and a record of say, a hundred previous games (and of course, food and water). After a period of five days, the child would walk out of the room as a pretty good chess player. In our analogy, the...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 05:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/machine-learning-for-stock-market-investment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/machine-learning-for-stock-market-investment/</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Stock Market</category>
        
        <category>Support Vector Machine</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evacuated Tube Collectors</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Renewable energy is the key for the planet’s existence in the future. The fossil fuels are non-renewable and require finite resources, which are dwindling because of high cost and environmentally damaging retrieval techniques. Climate change is real. Global warming is real. It took some time to accept this hard fact, but now with the realization, production of clean energy has become the primary goal of countries across all continents.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Great amount of research is carried in improving the efficiency of renewable energy and making it inexpensive. The main objective is to minimize or eliminate the usage of electricity...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 05:30:30 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evacuated-tube-collector/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/evacuated-tube-collector/</guid>
        
        <category>Energy</category>
        
        <category>Renewables</category>
        
        <category>Thermal Sciences</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Halting Problem</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you have written computer codes, then you certainly would have fallen into the trap of infinite loops. Then you might have wondered if there is an algorithm to check if any given computer program runs into an infinite loop or not; in other words, to check if it halts or not. How wonderful it would be if such an algorithm exists! But alas, the truth is that there is no such algorithm, not because no one has found such an algorithm yet, but because there is no way of finding such an algorithm ever.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;halting problem&lt;/strong&gt;...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 02:06:15 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-halting-problem/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/the-halting-problem/</guid>
        
        <category>Complexity theory</category>
        
        <category>Logic</category>
        
        <category>Mathematics</category>
        
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Design of Aircraft Windows</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everything in an aircraft you see is for a reason. Nothing is there coincidentally. And one such thing is the shape and design of the windows.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With increase in commutation through flights, the aeroplanes started flying at higher altitudes, since lesser air density meant lesser drag which directly affected fuel efficiency. Also turbulence due to atmosphere is less. But some modifications had to be done to make the conditions safe for the passengers at high altitudes. So, a pressurized cabin was introduced into the flights. This pressurized cabin keeps the interior of the flight at a higher pressure compared to...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 22:35:21 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/design-of-aircraft-windows/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/design-of-aircraft-windows/</guid>
        
        <category>Aeronautics</category>
        
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How QR code was invented</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-qr-code-was-invented&quot;&gt;How QR code was invented&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Denso Wave a subsidiary of the Toyota Group are attributed with the creation of the QR Code back in 1994. Originally it was used to track parts in the vehicle manufacturing industry, but its use and scope has since grown tremendously. One of the main objectives when creating the QR Code was to come up with a new barcode that allowed more data to be encoded without increasing the size (dimensions / surface area) of existing barcodes. This was achieved by including a second dimension.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The QR Code was born.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;working-of-qr-code&quot;&gt;Working of QR...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 22:07:21 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-qr-code-was-invented/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/how-qr-code-was-invented/</guid>
        
        <category>QR code</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Smart Grid</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;How many times have you felt guilty about excessive usage of electricity when you see your monthly bill? Imagine managing the electricity delivered to your house like you manage activities like personal banking from a computer!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You will no longer have to wait till the end of the month to know how many units you have consumed- you have “Smart meters,” and other mechanisms, will allow you to see how much electricity you use, when you use it, and its cost. It also comes with real-time pricing, which will allow you to save money by using less power...</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-grid/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ieeenitk.org/blog/smart-grid/</guid>
        
        <category>Smart grid</category>
        
        <category>Electric grid</category>
        
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
