<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A blog about our findings and musings</title>
    <description>IEEE NITK is a student branch of IEEE located at NITK Surathkal. This blog serves as a collection of ideas and thoughts of different members in various technical areas.</description>
    <link>/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 02:18:24 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 02:18:24 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice on Computer Science - Vinay Bhat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/vinay_bhat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vinay Bhat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-do-you-think-should-be-done-in-college-to-enhance-your-resume&quot;&gt;Q. What do you think should be done in college to enhance your resume?&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ans: One should Work hard to get a high GPA. An important aspect is to work on side projects as well-course projects or your own projects. Small projects help you understand and complete learning. It is ideal to contribute to Big Open Source repositories to understand big projects. Best thing is to try to leverage these projects into your first internship. It is more important to learn one language properly rather than every langauge and not master any one of...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/vinay-bhat-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/vinay-bhat-interview/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Internships</category>
        
        <category>Career Advice</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to IEEE-NITK Chapter</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;IEEE is the world’s largest professional association advancing innovation and technological excellence for the benefit of humanity. IEEE and its members inspire a global community to innovate for a better tomorrow through its highly-cited publications, conferences, technology standards, and professional and educational activities. IEEE is the trusted “voice” for engineering, computing and technology information around the globe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;IEEE is incorporated under the Not-for-Profit Corporation Law of the state of New York. It was formed in 1963 by the merger of the Institute of Radio Engineers (IRE, founded 1912) and the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE, founded 1884).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;beginning-of-ieee-nitk&quot;&gt;Beginning...</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 05:02:44 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/introduction-to-ieee/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/introduction-to-ieee/</guid>
        
        <category>IEEE NITK</category>
        
        <category>CompSoc</category>
        
        <category>Piston</category>
        
        <category>Diode</category>
        
        
        <category>IEEE</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
